<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lyttle treatyse called the image of idlenesse conteynynge certeyne matters moued betwene Walter Wedlocke and Bawdin Bacheler. Tra[n]slated out of the Troyane or Cornyshe tounge into Englyshe, by Olyuer Oldwanton, and dedicated to the Lady Lust.</title>
            <title>Image of idleness.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107597</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843295</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843295</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15297</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14893)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15297)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1588:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lyttle treatyse called the image of idlenesse conteynynge certeyne matters moued betwene Walter Wedlocke and Bawdin Bacheler. Tra[n]slated out of the Troyane or Cornyshe tounge into Englyshe, by Olyuer Oldwanton, and dedicated to the Lady Lust.</title>
                  <title>Image of idleness.</title>
                  <author>Oldwanton, Oliver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[104] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By wyllyam Seres, dwellynge in Powles Churche yard at the signe of the Hedgehogge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1556].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from: Pincombe, M. Date of the "Image of idleness" (Notes and queries, March 1994, p. 21).</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border (McK. &amp; Ferg. 55); initial.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Erotic literature, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15297:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A lyttle treatyſe called the Image of Idleneſſe, conteynynge certeyne matters moued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene Walter wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke and Bawdin Bacheler. Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the Troyane or Cornyſhe tounge into Englyſhe, by Olyuer Old wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and dedicated to the Lady Luſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:15297:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15297:2"/>
            <head>The Table of this preſent boke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe preface of the tranſlatour. Capi. i. The fyrſt part of a certeyne Epiſtle ſent by Bawdyn Bacheler to Walter Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, wherin doth apeare the grounde that cauſed the ſettynge forth of this treatyſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Capitulo .ii.</item>
               <item>¶ Bawdyn Bacheler beinge ſuter to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne Gentylwoman for maryage, wryteth to a frende of hers for to haue his helpe and furtheraunce in the matter. Capi. iii.</item>
               <item>¶ Wheras Bawdin had bin ſuter to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne Gentylwoman for maryage, and was in good hope to obteyne, he receaued know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge to the contrary by letter from a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman that hadde byn partely a meanes for hym, and therupon wrote backe to the ſaid Gentleman as foloweth. Capi. iiii.</item>
               <item>¶ Here Bawdyn wryteth to the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman mencioned in the laſt letter. Ca. v.</item>
               <item>¶ Where as a certeyne Gentlewoman bare in hande that ſhe was determyned neuer to mary, and was neuertheleſſe lykely to be much ſued vnto for maryage, here Bawdyn informeth her by his letter vnder what ſort ſhe were beſte to vſe and gyue ouer her ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Capitulo .vi.</item>
               <item>¶ Here Bawdyn wryteth to a certeyne gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tlewoman
<pb facs="tcp:15297:3"/>that was daungerous to be ſene or ſpoken withal by ſuch as came to ſue vn to her for maryage. Capi. vii.</item>
               <item>¶ Here Bawdyn wrytethe to a certeyne Gentlewoman at whoſe handes he had bin diſdeynefully refuſed vppon treatye of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryage. Capitulo .viii.</item>
               <item>¶ Here Bawdyn wryting to a certeyne gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tleman his frende, amonge other thynges bewayleth hym ſelfe of his euyll ſpeede in wooynge and treaty of maryage. Capi. ix.</item>
               <item>¶ Where as Bawdyn ſerued in Garryſon and had compounded with a certeyne gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, his frende, to repayre thyther at all tymes of daunger, the ſame being ſo ſtreyghted in a tyme of commotion, that he was forced for his ſafegard to take another howlde, where as were many Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whiche furnyture the other greattly wanted. Here Bawdyn maketh hym ryqueſt to haue ſome fruition of that commoditie. Capitulo .x.</item>
               <item>¶ The aunſwere made to the ſayde letter. Capitulo .xi.</item>
               <item>¶ Here Bawdyn replyeth to the foreſayde anſwere, and percuing his continual euyll ſpede, doth determyne to gyue ouer all ſuch kynde of ſutes. Capi. xii.</item>
               <item>¶ The ſeconde parte of the Epyſtle ſent by
<pb facs="tcp:15297:3"/>Bawdyn Bacheler to Walter Wedlocke. Capitulo .xiii.</item>
               <item>¶ Here Bawdyn to proue that women are neuer ſo much addyet or bent to theyr owne wyll and opynyon, but that by wyſedome and good pollycy they may eaſely be broken therof, ſheweth a lyuely example of late ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. Capi. xiiii.</item>
               <item>¶ The thyrde and laſt parte of the Epyſtle ſent by Bawdyn Bacheler to Walter Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke. Capitulo .xv.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶ Here endeth the Table.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15297:4"/>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The preface of the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour. Capitulo primo.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶ To the ryght honorable and his eſpeciall good Lady, the lady Luſt of Paweſforde, Olyuer Oldwanton, your Ladyſhips bondeman, wyſſheth a ioyfull lyfe and contynuall felicitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Allynge to mynde the oppi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Ariſtippus, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne Philoſopher of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picuriens ſecte, who by pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>founde argumentes and ſundry authorities vſed to maynteyne, that it was lawefull for man and woman at vacante tymes to exerciſe them ſelues with kyſſinge and imbraſynge (together with the ſuites and cerymonies thereunto belongynge) ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to ſyt ſtyll and be idle. The ſame my ioly good Lady hath cauſed me ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to deteſt the wicked vice of Idlenes, that in eſchewynge therof I haue had ſundry de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyſes, howe I myght moſt conueniently be occupyed, and thereupon fyndynge my ſelfe more apte then able, for thexcerciſe afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde. And moreouer aſwell ignoraunte in euery crafte and facultie of bodely labour as
<pb facs="tcp:15297:4"/>deſtitute both of lernynge and knowledge, wherby to inuente or ſet forthe any worthy matter of newe. I determined at length bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue vnderſtandynge in ſundrye tounges, to take vpon me the tranſlation of ſome worke into Englyſhe, and for that pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe, peruſing a numbre of bookes, I chaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced to fynde a lyttle queare intiteled, the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Idleneſſe, wrytten many yeres paſt in the Troyane or Cornyſhe ſpeache, beinge the mother tounge of this noble Realme, then called Bryttayne, which made me the more wyllynge to take the ſame in hande, thynkynge that it myght drawe ageyne to memory the valyaunt people of Troy, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of for my parte (be it ſpoken without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uante) I am one of the worthy ofſpringe. But then came to my remembraunce the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of Plato, who ſayth, that man lyueth not chiefely for hym ſelfe, but rather for his contrey, meanyng that we ſhulde not apply our trauel or ſtudy to our priuate pleſure or commoditie: but rather to thaduauncement of our common wealth: which this purpoſe ſemed not to concerne, and therefore myght chaunce by ſome mens opynion ought not to be traueyled on. Yet neuertheleſſe lyke as commonly moſt men be not ſone perſwaded to gyue ouer the thinge that they are affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onated
<pb facs="tcp:15297:5"/>vnto, vppon any ſurmyſe or report, that the doinge therof ſhulde ſtande ageynſt the rule of good order: But rather to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie theyr cauſe, wyll ſerche for ſome colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable argument to proue that the ſame maye ſtande within the compaſe of order. Euen ſo I beinge bent to this tranſlation, (with the helpe of my wyttes which in this caſe fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoured my wil) haue vnder ſuch ſort wreſted common reaſon, that in mine opinion (being inoughe as I ſuppoſe for the diſcharge of myne owne conſcience) the doynge thereof may well inough ſtande with the precept of Plato. If not indirectely, yet at the leaſte way by a meanes which I proue as thus.</p>
               <p>To be a ſtudient of the lawes, a councellour or a miniſter in the common welth is well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with Plato, and then to encorage or aſſiſt ſuch perſon in his ſtudye or miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, muſt nedes be of lyke effecte. And that in my mynde ſhalbe accomplyſſhed in this worke. For it is apparant vnto vs, that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and ſadde ſtudye which perteyneth to the gouernaunce and miniſtration in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com wealth is ſo contrary to moſt mens na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that if the mynd be not recreated with ſome pleaſaunt matter, the wyttes wyl ſone appalle, and the lyuely ſpirites waxe feble or dull. And therefore it ſemeth (that as it
<pb facs="tcp:15297:5"/>is neceſſarie) to haue ſtudentes councellers and miniſters in a common wealth. Euen as neceſſary it is that ſome men ſhulde trauell to ſet forth ſuch matter as may reuiue theyr ſpirites, beynge mortyfyed by contynuall graue ſtudye, which otherwyſe as accloyed and werye, ſhulde of force be dryuen by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aptnes, to ceaſe in theyr ſtudy or miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſurely Madame, the iniquitie of tyme is nowe ſuche: that the verye graueſte and moſte wyſe ſorte of men (yea and euen they which haue miniſtration in the common wealth) wyll ſometyme ſooneſt laughe and reioyce to here and rede euyll of women: yet not as thoughe beinge euyll marched theym ſelues, they ſhulde ſeme gladde to perceaue other men in lyke caſe, as yf the euyll were as common as women are great in numbre, or that they thynke that they maye by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of bookes more ſafely reproue theyr wiues faultes then by expreſſe wordes. But rather commeth as a certeyne plage of light<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes or franzie by thoperation of ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers planet, or euyll humoure that cauſeth them indiſcretly to condempne them ſelues, by defamynge theyr moſte naturall and beſt knowen parente. Lyke as yf the Tercell wolde ſaye that his Ceryer or dame were a Puttocke or Kyte, which argueth him ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:15297:5"/>neuer likely to proue good hauke: And euen ſo it is of theſe madde men that delyght to ſpeake and here euyll of women. Howebeit nowe very ſhortly, when by the beneuolence of the bodyes aboue, there ſhal no more ſuch occaſions be myniſtred. I doubte not but that men wyl amende their miſreportes and gyue ouer ſuch vnſemely delectations. But yet in the meane ſeaſon it ſhalbe neceſſarye to ſerue the tyme. And therefore the matter of this tranſlation beinge interlaſed with certeyne ſurmyſed faultes ageynſte women, ſemeth to be as an ayde to the miniſters in a common wealth, to refreſhe with all theyr wyttes, beinge as I ſayde before, appalled with graue ſtudye. So that whereas ſuche miniſters by theyr ſtudy and trauell do ſerue the common wealth indirectly: Euen ſo by this worke, which tendeth to meinteine and continewe theyr wyttes apte for ſtudye and miniſtration. Me thinketh I ſerue the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon wealth by a meanes, ſo that my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyle herein maye well inoughe ſtande with the precepte of Plato. And that thereby at the leaſte way I Hall deſerue as much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, as the Smyth which maketh a wreſt to tune thinſtrument: Who although he be ignorant in muſicke, is yet worthy of ſome thankes for tharmony, by reaſon that
<pb facs="tcp:15297:6"/>and yf his traueyle had not bin, the ſtringes coulde not haue binne brought to agree in tune, and then had there byn no melody at al. But alas, a lamentable caſe to remember howe the folly and malyce of man is encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſyth the dayes of Saynt Iohn the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt, who for his recreation after longe prayers (as theſe diſcrete old wiues beare in hande) vſed to refreſhe hym ſelfe in playing with his byrde. And lykewyſe holy Saynt Anthony in teachynge his lyttle Pygge to tumble and vaulte, and dyd not delyght to here or vnderſtande of womens faultes or doublenes, as men do nowe a dayes, which alteration by thoppinion of ſome doctours, commeth by thinfluence of ſome diſordered planet. As in deede Venus of late to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce her ſelfe haſted her ordinarie courſe, thinkynge to make her aſcendaunte aboue the heade of Iupiter, but by a miſchaunce ſhe ſtumbled on Scorpio, and vnder ſuche ſorte was tangled, that not onely ſhe fayled thaduantage of her pretended purpoſe, but moreouer loſt two degrees, and halfe of her poſſeſſed preemynence, the reuoluſyon wherof ſemeth to be a great part of the cauſe that maketh many women nowe adayes to ſtraye out of order, and miniſter much occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of euyll reporte, as couetynge to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpted
<pb facs="tcp:15297:7"/>of hygher eſtate and abilitie then in dede they are, or in makynge theyr bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and come<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yneſſe ſeme more then it is, to garnyſhe them ſelues with more ſumptuous apparell and coſtely Iewels then dothe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteyne. For the meyntenaunce whereof, they abuſe that parte of theyr bodies where as the ſigne of Scorpio dothe commonly raigne, and by ſuch meanes for a tyme ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth well theyr purpoſe, and doth increaſe theyr preferment and eſtimation. Howebeit at length eyther by ſmellynge or ſuſpicion, they fall into defame and oblequy of the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, and be leſſe eſtemed or ſet by then when they fyrſt began. But what ſoeuer the cauſe of ſuche alteration be. Sythen I perceane that men are nowe ſo peruerſly bente to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and here euyll of women, yet for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and zeale that I beare vnto all wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, I haue thought beſt, bicauſe they may be the redier with theyrs anſwere or excuſe, if any of theym ſhall happen to be charged with any of the faultes or euyll properties mencioned in this booke. For to make them fyrſt priuie thereunto, by directynge of this my ſimple worke vnto your Ladyſhyppe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of all honorable women in theſe dayes (none diſcommended) aſwell for ſinguler wyt and good conueyghaunce, as for great
<pb facs="tcp:15297:7"/>pollicie and longe experience coumpted moſt notable, not doubtynge but that all women by your Ladyſhyppes good aduyſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, wyll be well able to defende or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them ſelues, what ſo euer ſhalbe layde to theyr charge, which chiefely hath holde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me to brynge this matter into our vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſpeche, accoumptynge more honour for then to haue it come in queſtion and be well aunſwered, then by ſcylence to let it alway remayne in ſuſpicion or doubtfull. In the furtheraunce wherof yf it may lye in me ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by my wordes or weapon, to do them any ſeruice or pleaſure: be theyr cauſe right or wronge, I am and ſhalbe both theyr ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate and champion tyll my lyues ende.</p>
               <p>For doubtleſſe Madame, I hadde rather a thouſande men ſhulde peryſhe by the felynge of theyr faultes (yf any ſuch were) then that I wolde defame or condempne the very ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſt woman of your Ladyſhyppes trayne, by confeſſynge of ought that might make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geynſte her. And for my trauetyle and good wyll in this behalfe do requyre nothynge els at your Ladyſhyppes handes, but only that after this tranſytory lyfe, when your good Ladyſhyppe for your woorthy workes in earth, ſhalbe glorified in the celeſtial throne of the goddeſſe Venus, that I may be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:15297:8"/>ageine to youth, and made page of your Ladyſhyppes Chamber, &amp; that in the meane tyme it may pleaſe your Ladyſhippe notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandynge the debilitie of my body, yet for the myghtyneſſe of my mynde and ſkylfull practyſe, to admytte me Captayne generall of your bande, which I doubt not, what by mine owne pollycies, and what by the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and ſecrete ſhyftes of mine expert He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauldes, and circumſpecte eſpialles ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſedly to leade and gouerne, as they ſhall eſcape all reproche and daunger of theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes. And as for the ſafegarde of theyr ſoules, bicauſe it concerneth not the charge of that office, I wyl referre the ſame to frier Floyſterar, your Ladyſhyppes Penitence, who for a ſmall portion of the ſpoyle (as ſome folke bere in hande) wyll take theyr whole peryll on hym ſelfe, as beſte knowethe the blacke Prouinciall, who longe preſerue your good Ladyſhyppe, and proſper your procea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges for euer and euer Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15297:8"/>
               <head>The Image of Idleneſſe. ¶ The fyrſte parte of a certeyne Epiſtle ſent by Bawdyn Bacheler to Walter Wedlocke, wherin doth appeare the grounde that cauſed the ſettynge forthe of this Treatyſe. Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo .ii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Oodman Wedlocke my harty commendations layde apart, wheras I perceaue by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Thomas Talker your Secretary that ye ſaye it is a ſhame for me to be ſo longe tyme vnmaryed, affirmynge that I deſpyſe and eſchewe maryage, as a carefull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiete lyfe, beinge good for nothynge els but onely to brynge ſinfull people, that can paciently here it to heauen by the penaunce therof, as the very ſelfe purgatory that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lerned men haue ſo longe time contended vpon. Doubtleſſe Walter I do marueyle muche what hath moued you to charge me with ſo great an iniquitie, as that I ſhulde diſpraiſe the bleſſed Sacrament of matrimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye, being inſtituted by God hym ſelfe, the very ground and ſomme of al goodnes, yea and that is of ſuche perfection, that if any mortal man had inuented the ſame, he ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:15297:9"/>thereby haue worthely deſerued immortall prayſe and fame, the groundes therof are ſo commendable and neceſſary. Nor ſurely I neuer hadde other then very good and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent opinion of it in all my lyfe, and yet in dede Walter I dayly ſe and haue ſayd that wedded men for the more parte haue alway woful and cumbrous lyues, vpon groundes and occation miniſtred by theyr wynes. But for very trothe by the defaulte and negly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of them ſelues, that commonly lacketh eyther grace or diſcretion to order and vſe theyr wyues as they ſhuld do. Which neuer theleſſe is not to be marueyled at, for ſurely the ryght feate therof is a ſecrete that God reueleth not to all men, left then they ſhulde lyue in ſuch continuall pleaſauntneſſe and felicitie that they wolde neuer wyllyngly de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parte this lyfe: whiche by thopinion of the Vtopyans is a great ſuſpecte of perdicion, but as for me in dede I haue the gyft ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And therfore I enſure you, haue bin ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry deſyrous to mary. Yet not ſo muche for mine owne commoditie, as for that I wold gyue other men example how to vſe and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne theyr wyues in the ryght ſort, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to expell the inconuenience that I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue doth enſue by the contrarye, but my chaunce hath not bin to obteyne. For the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyll
<pb facs="tcp:15297:9"/>uyll to e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mpeſſhe ſo good a purpoſe of quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the worlde by one meanes or other, hath alwayes hyndred my ſuite, whiche is the very cauſe that I am ſo longe tyme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maryed, and for no ſuch errour or euyll opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion as ye haue vntruly ſurmyſed of me, for the more playne declaration whereof, I haue herewithall, ſent you a note or copye of ſuch letters as with careful hart I wrote before this vnto dyuers to entreate for my ſelfe vppon maryage, whiche when ye haue peruſed, then wyll I declare vnto you fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of my mynde in this behalfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Here Bawdyn Bacheler beinge fuſet t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a certeyne Gentlewoman for maryage, wryteth to a frende of hers for to haue his helpe and furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce therein. The thyrde Chapter.</head>
               <p>AFter my very harty commendation, ye ſhall vnderſtande that partly for mine owne comforte and commoditie, know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge by ſundry meanes what ioyes and feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie there maye be in maryage: and partely moued of compaſſion, perceauynge a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of men ignorantly abuſynge them ſelues in orderynge of theyr wyues (whiche by my
<pb facs="tcp:15297:10"/>good enſample myght be reformed) lyue in miſerie and great vnquietneſſe: I am vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determined with all ſpede to be a maried man, but yet not myndynge to beſtowe my ſelfe ſo vnaduiſedly, for any haſte, as to chooſe a wyfe for couetiſe of goodes or land whereas my harte wyll not ſerue me to loue and fauour the perſon: nor for dotyng loue or fauour, where as there is not ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient abilitie in ſubſtaunce towarde ſuche charges as foloweth maryage: nother yet for both where as the age ſhall much dyffer from mine owne. Whiche thynges circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly conſydered, I iudge them all accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to my hartes deſyre, with a number of good conditions to be ioyned together in myſtres B. your kynſwoman, to whome of late I haue bin ſuter in that behalfe, and do perceaue by ſundry meanes, that ſhe wyl fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe your aduyce. Wherfore ſyr I ſhal ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry hartely deſyre you to haue your helpe and furtheraunce therin. Whiche to recompence (yf my ſute take place) I dare be bolde to promyſe you a thouſande thankes of her part, for the ſpedynge of her to ſo good a huſbande, as by my demeanoure towardes her I entende to ſhewe my ſelfe. And yet for all that, I haue ſuch diſpayre and miſtructe in the matter, that do the beſt ye can, I wyl
<pb facs="tcp:15297:10"/>wage with you forty pounde that I get her not, and on my fidelitie pay you truly yf I leſe. I learned this wager of a crafty prieſt that by ſuch meanes with loſynge of a lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle money, wan a good bynefice. Lyke as for my parte I truſt in this caſe to leſe and yet be a geyner, as knowethe the maker of matrimonie, whom I wolde gladly had ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>what enterlaſed the pleaſaunce therof with ſome coller or bytterneſſe, for feare leſt the continuall caſe and quietneſſe that I ſhall fynde therin, ſhulde happen to cauſe me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and forget to wyſhe and worke for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Wheras Bawdyn had byn ſuter to a cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyne Gentlewoman for maryage, and was in good hope to obteyne, he receaued knowledge to the contrary by letter from a Gentleman, that hadde partly bin a meane for hym, &amp; therupon wrote backe as foloweth. The fourth Chapter.</head>
               <p>AFter my ryght harty commendations, ye ſhall vnderſtande that I haue recea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued your letter conteynynge a determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate nay in my ſute to the Gentlewoman ye
<pb facs="tcp:15297:11"/>wote of, whiche with a forced pacience I am contented to accepte accordyngely. And in perſwadyng my ſelfe the eaſelyer to bere the ſame, do conſider that and if my deſyre had byn graunted, the one of vs ſhulde of ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſitie (beinge borne ſo farre a ſunder) haue bin conſtrayned to abandon and forſake our countrey and kynrede, whereby myght en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue to vs both more vnquietneſſe, then any commoditie therof growynge wolde be able to counteruayle.</p>
               <p>With this and lyke coniectures, I am nowe faine to feade my phantaſie of entent to make lyght what lyeth at my hart moſte heauye. The deuyll I thynke, for deſpyte cauſed me nowe (contrarye to my common wont) to tender ſuch ſute ſo earneſtly: other els God hath appoynted it as my penaunce for that I haue oftentymes treated much of lyke matter, whereas in harte I mente no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng leſſe, which requireth by conſequence of equitie to mynd much and be lyttle regar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as nowe it foloweth. And yet to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumpt indifferently, me thinketh I can not well aſcrybe it to neyther of them both, but all wholy to my ſelfe, that entendynge by pollycie to expel (as it were) a ſmarte, haue conceaued a continuall ache. As thus, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentynge the loſſe of my verye frende hee
<pb facs="tcp:15297:11"/>late huſbande, whiche to my harte was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> leſſe ſorowful, then yf mine owne lyfe ſhuld immediatly haue folowed, I thought that yet yf I myght get ſome commoditie by his death, that dyrynge his lyfe tyme, coulde not be obteyned: the comforte of the one wolde ſo quallifie the griefe of the other, that it ſhulde the more eaſely and ſooner be diſgeſted. And thereupon dyd conſyder that the moſte ſoueraygne iewell in this worlde (which many men myſſeth) is to haue a wife of commendable qualities and conuerſation. Wherof ſhe (as I had knowen by the report of hym, whoſe iudgement beinge grounded on experience, was not to be doubted) dyd appeare to be one. And therfore to recoue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her as my recompence, was the original and onely cauſe of my ſute at the fyrſt vnto her. Whiche ſythens by circumſtaunces dyd en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to ſuch preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pcion of ſpede (in mine opinion) that I accompted her as obteined. And therewithall pacyfyenge my former tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, as counterpoyſed with the ſame, dyd reuyue my mortyfyed ſpirites with the bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes, wherof fewe men fyndeth the fruite, &amp; accepted her in harte none other but as a member or parcell of my ſelfe. Which nowe beinge concluded contrary, can to me be no leſſe peynefull, then the loſſe of mine hands
<pb facs="tcp:15297:12"/>or any other lymme of mine owne body, the langour wherof is incredible to be wrytten. Thus doth it nowe apeare what it is to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tende ageynſt the deuine purueyaunce, as in murmurynge ageynſte the hande of Godde, (whiche we lyttle knowe for what well or wo it is mente) to go aboute the alteration therof by worldely pollicie, whiche for the more parte turneth to our owne harme. As enſample by my ſelfe that entended to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyde the ſmarte that I haue doubled.</p>
               <p>Wherefore from henceforth my councell and practiſe ſhalbe in felicitie not to preſume, nor in aduerſitie to diſpayze, neyther yet to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy our wyttes for to ſeke the alteration of neyther, but with humble ſpirite ſuffer the gouernour to proceade, truſtynge all to be for the beſt, as in dede for my parte nowe in this extremitie and peruerſeneſſe of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, I fynd the ſame by experience, for by the myſſynge of my mynde, mine affection is altered into meditacion, whereby I do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider both his power and mine owne weke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, more then before tyme I dyd. And therewithall as the beſt thynge that I may perceaue to haue obteyned by this my ſute and enterpryſe, I ſatyffie my ſelfe not thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge my trauell and good wyll to be ſpent all in vayne, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15297:12"/>
               <head>Of Idleneſſe. ¶ Here Bawdyn wryteth to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tlewoman mencioned of in the laſt letter. The fyfth Chapter.</head>
               <p>Bycauſe I am loth to beſtowe more kind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes on you, then of your parte ſhall thankefully be accepted, I haue me commended euen as hartely and as often as beſt can content your mynde and none other wyſe. Lo nowe may ye perceaue what a pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable and louyng huſbande ye myght haue of me, if ye had bin happy, for hereby doth apeare that I loue not to beſtowe any thing in waſt, and yet the ſame notwithſtanding, to ſatiſfye your phantaſie, can be contented to giue you libertie ouer the threaſure of my harte, to ſpende therof at your owne wyll and pleaſure. Further you ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande that I haue receaued your refuſe con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernynge my late ſute vnto you, whiche on the one pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te bicauſe it doth ſo much contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty my deſyze, ought not in reaſon to be a lyttle mine vnquietnes of mynd. But yet on the other ſyde, conſiderynge that ſuche is your wyll and pleaſure, whiche I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes determined to preferre and folowe a boue mine owne, I can but accept it in good parte, and be contented therewith, and for the tyme wyl no more trouble you with any
<pb facs="tcp:15297:13"/>further requeſt in that behalfe, as in deede there is good cauſe why, for as I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande ye are alredy els where promyſed, wherof God ſende you ioy. And as for my parte if reaſon in me do not the rather ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due affection, I entende to practiſe the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon prouerbe, which ſayth that newe loue dryueth away olde ſorowes. But ſurely it ſhalbe done all by proteſtation, that ye fall not wydowe ageyne, for and if ye do, I wil ones more attempt you, what ſo euer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe ſhall happen to paſſe me in the meane tyme, truſtynge to ſpede neuer the worſe at your handes, though nowe for certeyne con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiderations I ſeme to take the miſſinge of your good mynde lyghter then inwardely I feele it.</p>
               <p>Further concernynge my deare frende your notable late huſbande, lyke as it is not poſſible to recouer ageyne his body, ſo were it iniury to ſuffer his deſerued good fame pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſhe. For the preſeruation wherof I haue here Sithall ſent certeyne verſes in maner of an Epytaph, which I pray you cauſe to be grauen and fixed on his ſepulture, and thus hartely fare ye well.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ The Epytaph.</head>
                     <l>Lewes lyeth here, ſo fell his fatall houre</l>
                     <l>Blethin ſurnamed, of ſouth wales the floure</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:15297:13"/>
                     <l>In knowledge of the lawe, worthy eternal fame.</l>
                     <l>In wyſedome and temperaunce, coequall to the ſame.</l>
                     <l>With all good qualities, ſhortly to conelude</l>
                     <l>And honeſte trade of lyfe moſte plenteouſly endude,</l>
                     <l>Whom cruel death alas, in his .xxxv. yeare</l>
                     <l>Waſtynge of this worlde, hath layde a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>longe on beare.</l>
                     <l>Wayle his want Welchmen, to rathe ebbed was his tyde.</l>
                     <l>God ſende you many ſuche, and lenger to abyde.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Where as a certeyne Gentlewoman bare in hande, that ſhe was determined neuer to mary, and was neuertheleſſe lykely to be muche ſued vnto for maryage, here Bawdyn informeth her by his letter, vnder what ſort ſhe were beſte to vſe and gyue ouer her ſuters. The ſyxt Chapter.</head>
               <p>GOod myſtres N. I commende me vnto you, beinge ryght ſory that I can not ſeaſon my commendations with ſome hartineſſe, howe be it I aſſure you it is not
<pb facs="tcp:15297:14"/>lefte vndone for any lacke of good mynde, but onely for that I am not as nowe maſter of mine owne harte, and can therfore in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge vtter any perfecte hartineſſe, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe yf it may do you any pleaſure to haue my harty commendations, ye maye be therin as it were your owne caruer. For doubtleſſe my harte is with you, ſo that ye maye vſe the office thereof euen as ye lyſte your ſelfe. And then hauinge the hart after ſuche ſort, it maye not be forborne but that the body muſt nedes be at your commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And if ye doubt the contrary on my behalfe, I praye you commaunde me to do what lately ye denyed me of, and then the trueth wyll apeare. Further, where as ye refuſe to accept me in mariage: yet not for any miſlykinge as ye ſay, but onely for that ye are vtterly determyned neuer to mary: Surely I accompte my ſelfe more bounden vnto you, for that gentle anſwere with your frendely enterteynemente beſydes, then I ſhulde be to ſome other for the grauntynge my whole requeſt, &amp; therfore if in any thyng I may do you ſeruice or pleaſure, ye ſhalbe well aſſured therof. And as a proofe or er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt peny of the ſame, I wyll at this tyme be ſo bolde as ſomewhat to councell you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernynge ſuch matter as, I ſuppoſe ye haue preſently moſte nede to be well aduyſed of
<pb facs="tcp:15297:14"/>which is (ſyth as ye ſaye ye are determined neuer to mary) ſomewhat to ſhewe you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what maner is ſhalbe beſt for you to vſe, and giue ouer ſuch as may happen to ſue vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you for mariage. Which kynde of ſuters ye ſhall vnderſtande are deuided in three ſun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dry ſortes. The one ſueth for loue of the perſon, another for loue of her lyuynge, and the thyrde are they that make of wooynge theyr paſtyme or recreation: practyſynge by ſutes at large done in ſport, howe to faſhion them ſelues and place theyr wordes ageynſt ſuch tyme as they ſhall happen to be earneſt ſuters in dede, and not meanynge to marry although theyr requeſt were graunted, but rather ſcoffyngly to retreate, and diſhoneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make theyr aduaunte of that they myght haue had. The diuerſitie and diſpoſitions of which perſons it ſhalbe neceſſary for you to endeuer your ſelfe with all the ſleyghtes and pollicie that poſſible ye maye deuyſe to perceaue and knowe, and thereafter to giue them enterteynement and anſwere.</p>
               <p>For as to any of the fyrſt ſort, a ſodayne refuſe is death without redemption, and therfore vnto ſuch you may not gyue the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe at fyrſte, but rather with an anſwere of double vnderſtandyng, by lyttle and lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle quayle theyr hope of ſpede: Or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe
<pb facs="tcp:15297:15"/>by counterfaytinge your ſelfe to be fro warde or entangled with ſome other euyll tatche, to make them thinke you better loſt then founde, ſo that they maye rather ſeme to gyue ouer then to be refuſed.</p>
               <p>But as for the ſeconde meyny (whereof God wote there are ſo many) ye can not vſe them to euyll. For ſurely vnto ſuche wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the very torment and payne of hel (ſo that the poore ſoule were ſaued) is ſcarſly ſufficient puniſhement. And therfore beſides an vtter nay at the fyrſt, to ſhewe them as much ſullayne ſtrangeneſſe as ye can deuiſe, whereby the rather to brynge them in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre of ſpede, ſhalbe but wel done: Reſpect yet ſomewhat to be had that ye ſeme not to take vnthankefully that whiche is offered vnder a frendly pretence, and beware that in ſuch caſe ye gyue no credyte to any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that ſpeaketh in theyr fauoure or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theraunce. For no doubt it is often ſene that ſuch ſutes grounded on couertiſe be ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with golde and gyftes, that manye tymes one frende ſelleth another, whereby bothe the byer and ſeller are geytners. But woe may be the poore wyfe that payeth for all, and yet is neuer the rather maryed, for in ſuch caſe the goodes be maryed, and not the woman, and as we may ſe by experience
<pb facs="tcp:15297:15"/>eyther of them cheryſhed and ſet by accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyngly.</p>
               <p>But nowe to the thyrde ſort of ſuters, theſe eluyſhe diſſemblers that I ſpake of be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, when ye haue a lyttle denyed them, whiche I wolde wyſhe were doone vnder a mylde indifferente ſorte, onely to eſchewe that ye miniſter them none occaſion to boaſt of any thynge graunted, and not to brynge them in vtter diſpayre of ſpede, wherby to gyue ouer theyr ſute and leſe no more but theyr laboure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For that were to lyttle pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, and therefore ye muſte in ſuche caſe when ye haue ſayde them nay, counteruayle your worde with a louynge lyppe or frendly eye, as though, not perceauynge theyr diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation, ye ment them muche better then ye ſpake, and therwithall to encreaſe theyr affection, ye muſt enterteyne them with port and faſhyon, as ye ſhall thynke moſt to theyr contentation, which neuertheleſſe muſte be done with ſuche demure ſimplicitie, as it ſeme not to paſſe the bowndes of woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed and honeſt eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and vnder ſo good awayte, that ye ſeme not in the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence to ſhewe the lyke grace and familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to any other: aſſayinge by ſuche meanes to make of ſuch counterfeytes ryght veneri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and then ſmylynge at theyr ſmarte,
<pb facs="tcp:15297:16"/>ſcornefully to gyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer, on my fayth I thinke in conſcience were none offence at al.</p>
               <p>I wryte you theſe thinges as a warning that ye recompence not the fayner with the faythfulles rewarde, nor marry away your lyuynge, and remayne wydowe your ſelfe for feare of repentaunce, as in dayes paſte, and not thynkynge thereby the rather to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure you (although I be one of the firſt ſort) to ſhewe me any grace or fauour. Yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theleſſe if any ſuch good chaunce happen me being for truth in my behalfe not loked for, and yet much truſted vpon, I aſſure you, ye ſhall gratifie your ſelfe with ſuche a good turne, as vpon the profe ye wyll be ſory to haue ſo longe tyme forborne, and ſo fare ye well.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Here Bawdyn wryteth to a certeyne Gentlewoman that was daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be ſene or ſpoken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all by her ſuters. The ſeuenth Chapter.</head>
               <p>MYſtres B. after my harty commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whereas ye vſe to abſente your ſelfe and wyll not be ſpoken withall at ſuche tyme as I and other good felowes come to treate with you vppon maryage, I
<pb facs="tcp:15297:16"/>can do no leſſe for good mynde that I beare you, but to wyſhe that ye wolde leaue ſuche demeanoure. For I aſſure you there are ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny men that gather euyl opinion therof, and thinke the cauſe to be that doubtynge your ſelfe to go with chylde, ye abaſhe to be ſene in any preſence of ſkilfull iudgement. How be it as for my parte, on my fayth I ſuſpect no ſuch thinge, but recken ſurely that ye do it onely of entent thereby to auoyde ſuters, whoſe preſence and wordes myght els hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to win you vnto wedding, by the which ye ſhulde leaue your chaſt wyddowyſhe lyfe, and leſe the merite that in heauen is for the ſame ordeyned. Howe be it, and if your meanynge be none other then ſo, then ſithe ye are ſo well aſſured in refuſynge of ſuche requeſtes, as before this I haue harde you bere in hande, better were in my mynd that ye common therof with as many as lyſt ſue vnto you, for the more temptacion ye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, the greater ſhalbe your mede. And yet bicauſe my lernyng in ſcripture doth not extende to diſcuſſe what blyſfull rewarde may be due for ſuch vnnaturall and frutles penaunce, the beſt and ſureſt way for you in my iudgemente were to accepte ſuche one of your ſuters to your huſbande or familiar frende, as ye may thynke loueth you moſte
<pb facs="tcp:15297:17"/>hartely, and in no wyſe to refuſe them all leaſt hereafter ye repent as other haue done. For what merite God gyueth to the chaſte ſowles I knowe not, but it is very certeine that the Goddeſſe Venus puniſheth ryght ſharpely the bodyes that are repugnaunt to her louynge lawes, as partely doth apeare by the hyſtories folowyng, which I tel you are not fayned, but wrytten by good auctho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie in the boke of Cupides ſayntes, and be thus. There was ſometyme a knyght na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Permalides that loued moſt hartely the Lady Agglaroſe, who for no ſute that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible myght be made, wolde aſcent to his de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyre. The importunate ſorowes whereof ſhulde ſhortely haue ended his wofull lyfe dayes, hadde not bin the greate mercy of Venus, who by playne miracle, pyteinge to ſe her faythfull ſeruaunt ſo tormented with the crueltie of a mercileſſe Lady, made an ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaunge of both theyr deſyres, ſo that this Lady loued this knyght aboue al creatures, and he to the contrary hated her beyonde al reaſon, whereupon when ſhe had longe time folowed him with many lamentable and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous complayntes requyrynge his fauoure and myght not obteyne, dyed euen of loue. Lo thus ye maye ſe Venus can wounde her diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſubiects with their owne wepon.
<pb facs="tcp:15297:17"/>There was alſo before this one Narciſſus, of ſuche bewtie and ſemelines, that dyuers women came out of farre countreys onely to beholde hym, wherof many peryſhed by his defaulte, for he wolde in no wyſe encline to loue, whiche cauſed Venus to take diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and to punyſhe hym as ye ſhall here. On a tyme this Narciſſus, to go in a diſguiſing with other companye, happened to attyre hym ſelfe in the apparell and garmentes of a woman, and paſſynge ouer a brydge, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued in the water the ſhadow of his owne comely perſon and ſtraunge attyre, whiche hym thought to be wonderfull ſemely, and thereupon for lacke of diſcretion to knowe hym ſelfe, whiche Venus withdrewe from hym, had no mynde on his diſguyſed appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, but iudged verely the ſame to be one of Dyanas Nymphes, who in ſuche lyke pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vſed oftentimes for recreation in the ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer ſeaſon to make her abode, and therup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon waxed ſo amorous of his owne ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, that after many humble requeſtes of loue, and inſtaunt deſyres of ſpeche, ſpede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he determined to refer hym ſelfe to her grace and mercy, ſaying that in ſo goodly a creature loue nor pitie coulde not be abſent, and then with armes diſplayed lepte into the ryuer, thynkinge to embrace his Lady,
<pb facs="tcp:15297:18"/>(who alſo helde her armes abrode of ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to his fonde opinion, onely for to receaue hym) and was there drowned. Thus was his crueltie rewarded with folly.</p>
               <p>There was alſo not longe agone in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa, both a knight and a Lady, who for the excellencie of theyr perſons and qualities, were of ſuch fortune, that dyuers ſued vnto them for loue, and coulde by no meanes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne. For not regardynge faythfull harte and good mynde, they couered ſo much high pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage &amp; great abilitie, that they thought none of theyr ſuters worthy to be accepted. The knyghtes name was Malmtrophus, and the Ladyes Syllera, who at length by thappoyntment of Venus fell both in loue, and were amorous eche of other. Then ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them called to remembraunce howe many ſuters they had ſuffered to peryſhe by theyr obſtinacy in loue before tyme. And thereuppon fell into deſpayre by remorce of conſcience, thinkyng verely that in ſo much as they had ſo miſuſed Venus lawes, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus from whom all grace to obteyne in loue doth preceade, wolde graunt them none, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were required and deuoutly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for. In ſo much that the one of them ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer durſte motion thother of loue, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes tormented them ſelues with inward
<pb facs="tcp:15297:18"/>deſyre and deſperate thoughtes, tyll at lengthe this Lady Syllera in folowyng the feminine nature, which of neceſſitie muſt by ſome meanes diſcloſe theyr ſecrete though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, wrought all her mynde and opynyon with ſylke in her ſampler, and ſone after dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed only of loue longing, wherof when Mal merophus had knowledge, and wyſt of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſampler, as enraged for ſorow, he ſtrangled hym ſelfe therwith and ſo miſerably ended. Thus for lacke of audacitie to diſcloſe theyr myndes eche to other (which grace for their ſtubburne boldenes in refuſynge of trewe louers before tyme, Venus withhelde from them, they dyed all bothe at miſchiefe, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che if it be well noted, is a greate enſample for other to eſchewe lyke offence in auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge the lyke or worſe punyſhement.</p>
               <p>Wherfore I wyll aduyſe you to accepte ſome one of your ſuters vnto your fauoure, and to leue this hardnes of hart in ſcorning theyr paynefull lyues. For doutles Venus is nowe of as great a power as euer ſhe was and as able to puniſhe her rebelles. yea and althoughe by her godly pacience ſhe ſpace you a ſeaſon vpon profe of amendement, yet maye you be ryght ſure, ſhe wyll at lengthe puniſhe you with ſome diſpleaſure if ye thus continu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Wherfore at your parell do as ye
<pb facs="tcp:15297:19"/>lyſt nowe that ye are warned, &amp; thynke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not that I wryte you theſe examples of inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ferre my ſelfe vnto your fauour, albeit that to my iudgement I am he that moſte loueth you. For ye haue ſo often denyed me that I am vtterly deſperate therein: as ſhortely wyll apeare by the ende of my wofull lyfe days for ſorowe of the ſame, which chaunce of all creatures ye ſhall haue moſte cauſe to lament. For thereby ſhall ye be ſure both to leſe a frende in earth, and to haue a ſhrewde Sollycitour in heauen. For when Venus ſhall enquire the cauſe of my ſodayne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge thyther, then muſte I nedes diſcloſe your obſtinate demeanour in loue, which no doubte wyll be extremely punyſhed, vnleſſe your amendement may apeare vpon ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the meane tyme. Or els and if your cruell hart be ſo ſtout that it wyll not alter for feare of her diſpleaſure and puniſhment, yet then let it alter in hope of her grace and fauour. For doubtleſſe ſhe is not ſo rigorous in punyſhynge her rebelles, but that ſhe is more benigne and gentle in cheriſhynge her faythful and obedient ſeruauntes. And ther fore in all holy ſcripture this is taken for her poſey or prouerbe, loue and lacke not, and if that be not inough to brynge her boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie in your credence, ye ſhall to affirme the
<pb facs="tcp:15297:19"/>ſame, here of a myracle whiche in the olde dayes ſhe wrought, and was thus. One Pigmalion, (a verye connynge grauer or workeman in ſtone and mettall) made in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labaſter the image of a woman whiche was of ſo goodly proportion, fauour, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce, that on a tyme as he behelde her he was ſodaynely taken with her loue, and that ſo feruently that he could not ſuffer to haue her out of his fyght. Whereuppon he bought her coſtely and ryche apparell, and dayly wold ſet hee at his table, carue to her of his beſt meates, at after none reade before her ſtoryes of loue, ſhewe her all his mynde in ſecrete cauſes, and at nyght take of her clothes and lay her by hym in naked bedde, greatly bewaylynge her deadly dombneſſe, and ſo continued a longe ſeaſon, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge the contrary councell of all his frendes. Which demeanoure the bleſſed Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus from aboue ryght well behelde, greatly commendynge his ſtedfaſt louynge courage, and to recompence the ſame, on a wynter nyght as he lay in his bedde, well nere fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen with embraſynge this colde image, ſhe gaue her naturall heate, lyfe, and quycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo that they were afterwardes maried together, and lyued longe tyme in blyſfull loue, and much ioy, tyll at length this Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malyon
<pb facs="tcp:15297:20"/>dyed, and then was his wife turned ageyne into an image of Alabaſter, whiche to this day ſo remayneth, and is accomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed through out all Greece theyr beſte and chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt pylgremage for to remoue or expell the paſſions and peynes of ielouſy, whiche for truth came fyrſt to knowledge and credence by this miracle. The princes of Tarent, but after ſome bookes of Ottronto, fyndynge her Lorde and huſhande in bedde with one of her Chamberers, fell into ſuche a maylyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coly and penſifeneſſe, that in maner ſhe was at the very poynt of death, and then beinge warned by a viſion to repayre vnto this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed image for helpe, dyd auowe her pylgry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage thyther, and receaued this oracle, (Marſoyſe thees duan Guiſea ancorne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>og hatre arta) being expounded by the preſtes of that temple to this effecte in Englyſhe.</p>
               <p>If to weare the horne thou fynde thy ſelfe agreu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. Gyue hym backe agaynt, and thou ſhalt ſone be eaſed. Whereby bothe ſhe and ſythens that tyme a great nomber of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beinge in lyke caſe haue byn wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully comforted and holpen. Wheras before the diſeaſe was in maner vtterly incurable. And ſurely all this is done by grace deryued from Venus. What creature then trowe ye may better ſpende theyr tyme then in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice
<pb facs="tcp:15297:20"/>of her that ſo benygnely rewardeth her faythfull ſeruauntes, doubtleſſe none. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore yet ones ageyne, as he that for al your vnkyndnes ſhewed, can bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wyſhe youwel, I wyll exhort you to enter and ſpende your lyfe in blyſfull loue, which vnfeyled amonge worldly felicities is the very greateſte ioye. Howbeit I ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke it not as he that hath had any experience therof, for alway it hath bin my chaunce to loue vnbeloued, whiche for truthe is the greateſt payne in earth, but yet the ſame maketh me perceaue in reaſon the blyſfulnes which may be in your loue, that are beloued: for of this I am certeyne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary circumſtaunce wyll haue contrary ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte, ſo that lyke as my loue is paynefull, bycauſe I am not beloued, euen ſo muſte yours nedes be pleaſaunt bicauſe ye are lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, wherefore enter into it hardely with a gladde harte, and that ye may well perſeuer in the ſame, ye ſhalbe aſſured of my daylye prayer, that ſometyme truſted to be of lyke religion, and nowe an abiecte al deſperate, but yet not by mine owne defaulte or deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge. Wherefore my truſte is that Venus wyll take at me no diſpleaſure, but at leaſt way recompence my well meanyng with the name of a Vencrian, whiche ſhalbe a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt tytle for me after this lyfe, to chalenge
<pb facs="tcp:15297:21"/>a tabernacle in her eternall throne. And nowe to conclude if ye ſhall thynke me wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be imputed of folly, for that I delare ſo much with ſuch paynted proces vppon ſo weake a grounde or matter, I pray you con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider therewithall that the newe wyne or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther troubled lycour, beinge in a cloſe veſſel wyll for lacke of ayer (if it be not vented) ſwell and bruſte his caſke. For euen ſo in lykewyſe my poore harte beinge repleniſhed with the anguyſhe of affection and deſyre, yf it ſhulde not thus by vtteringe of my mynde be ſuffred to aſſwage and eaſe it ſelfe, wold ouer ſwell with deadly ſighes, and ſhortely ſeuer in funder. And if ye be ſo harde of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that ye wyl not thinke al theſe things to be trewe, yet then I ſhall deſyre you at leaſt way to take them for your paſtyme in the readynge, as I haue done in the wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge. And ſo hartely fare ye well.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Here Bawdyn wryteth to a certeyne gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tlewoman at whoſe handes he had bin diſdeynefully refuſed vpon treaty of maryage. The .viii. Chapter.</head>
               <p>Myſtres G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>after my harty commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereas by your ſundry nayes
<pb facs="tcp:15297:21"/>vpon the ſute that before this I made vnto you for mariage, I was minded to giue vnto the ſame. Yet your gentle interteynemente at our laſt being together, when as ye graun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to common with me further therein at conuenient ſeaſon, &amp; after appoynted with my ſeruaunt both tyme and place of metyng for ſuch purpoſe, made me ſomewhat to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe my former intent, and to attende for you accordyngly, howe be it ye came not, which cauſed me (beinge then bownde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes Troynouant) to ſende a certeyne frende of myne to knowe the cauſe of your ſtay, vnto whom (not aunſwering the ſame) ye vnder a diſdeynefull ſorte vtterly refuſed me, which was more then neded to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of at that tyme, albeit that and if your fantaſy had ſerued you nedes ſo to do, yet me thynketh ye myght haue doone it with more temperaunce and leſſe wordes, lyke as it is poſſible inough I ſhulde haue done to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes you, yf ye had graunted my requeſt, in which caſe (on my faith) I am vncerteine whether I wolde haue taken or lefte, for I neuer vſe thorowely to examine my ſelfe therin, tyll tyme it apeare I maye be at the choyſe, and that neuer founde I at your handes. But and yf I had a gentle retreate with thankes for your confirmable good
<pb facs="tcp:15297:22"/>
mynd, had bin the leaſt of your recompence, and ſurely no leſſe I loked for on your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, ſpecially conſyderynge that women are or ſhulde be of a myld and gentle nature. And yet maye chaunce that your meanynge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, was better then to ſome mens iudge ment it ſounded, as thus. Perceauyng that myne affection towardes you was grounded on ſpeciall good opinion, which I had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued of you, ye doubted leaſte I ſhulde (euen to the death) lament the loſſe of ſuche a fauteleſſe wyfe, ſo greately deſyred, and therfore of intent to qualifie my griefe with the portion of my harme, ye haue ryght gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>telly aggrauaſed the one to mollyfie the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and contrary to your conuerſation for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced your tonge to declare you both ſtubborne of harte, ſuſpicious of imagination, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtance of mynde, that lyke as then all thinges conſidered, my loſſe was not great, my ſorowes ought not to be muche. And yf ye ment me ſo frindly, I am the more boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to thanke you, howe be it on my fayth to ſay trothe, I neded nothynge at all of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch confortatyues. For lyke as ſome men delyght for to trace the hare, more to perceaue the wylynes of her doublynge and ſubtyll ſkyppes, then for any ioye to recouer or brynge home the game: Ryght ſo in lyke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:15297:22"/>
for my parte, haue I vſed ſuch kynde of ſutes, more for my ſolace and recreation, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o vnderſtande the dealinge and demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of ſome folkes, then for any hope or intent to obteyne the thynge that I ſemed to ſeke for, as he that hath alwaſs thought the paſtyme of wooynge to be muche better then the penaunce of weddynge, or and if it myſhappen me at any tyme to be ouer deſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rous of ſpede therin, and in concluſion be denayed, whereby for lacke of good aduyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I chaunce a ſeaſon ſomwhat to lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t my repulſe, then in makynge conſolation to my ſelfe. I call to remembraunce a number of mine acquayntaunce, that vppon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>htey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge in lyke ſutes, whereas they ſought and loked for all ſuche commed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es as I haue iudged to be in you, when it came to the profe they had not onely myſt the ſame, but moreouer in the ſteade therof, found the clene contrary, with wonderful vnqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes and diſpleaſure, repentynge theyr ſpede al they lyfe dayes after, and tehn ſtreyght wayes do reioyce myne owne hap, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle theyrs, lyke as a man that hath eſca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped from a ſhypwracke, where many of his frendes peryſhed, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herwithall am clene out of hand delyuered from al ſuch thought and care as though I hadde neuer knowen
<pb facs="tcp:15297:23"/>
the partie, nor mynded ſuche matter. But yet for all theſe bragge, yf it ſhall ſeme vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you by the maner of my wrytynge, that I take ouer lyght the myſſing of your good mynde, yet wolde I be ryght ſory that ye ſhulde by the occaſion therof, eyther ſet the leſſe by your ſelfe (as to beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in dede the thing is no better worth) or yet to accumpt me ſo ignoraunte, that I can not eſteem thynges ſomewhat accordynge as they are. But rather thynke I pray you, the troth to be playne contrary on both partes, and that I wryte vnder ſuche ſorte eyther as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pollicie, to ſet lyttle by the thinge that can not be had, or els for that I doubte it myght diſteyne the grauitie which ſhulde be longe to the number of mine yeares, for to be acknowen any thinge intangled with the afflictions of loue, although that in dede it toucheth my very nere, or otherwyſe that I do it bycauſe I ſerue in Barriſon and place of warre, and wolde by the bolde bearynge out of ſuche a loſſe, ſhewe my ſelfe to be of ſuch hygh ſpirite and inuinſible harte, that I wyll not ſeme to be ouercommen with the thynge, whereunto bothe the myghtye and wiſe haue ſundry rymes giuen place, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the outward apparaunce of my weke and ſimple perſon, by counterfaytynge the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
<pb facs="tcp:15297:23"/>
vertue, after the opinion of ſome men called magnanimitie (temperately bearynge bothe felicitie and aduers fortune) I maye ſeme better worthy to ſupply the ſame, or better come, and ſo to aſſay whether by the ſpendynge of my good mynde vnrewarded, I may fynde meanes to obteyne better eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation then I haue deſerued, or at leaſte way if I myſſe of them bothe, yet thento quyet my ſelfe with the hope of the one, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in vayne. For doubtleſſe this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory life is intangled with ſo many kindes of miſerie, prouokynge penſiuenes, that vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe a man ſometyme wyll flatter him ſelfe with ſome kynde of vayne glory, or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the lyuely eye of his reaſon, delyght or reioyce in ſome one tryfle or other, the calamitie and vnquietneſſe therof, wyll ſo frette nature, that none ſhalbe able to lyue out half theyr naturall courſe, and therfore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it ſhall ſeme vnto you, that I might better haue ſpente the tyme then ſo to make ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, or thus to declare my ſelfe, yet bere ſo muche in my fauoure I beſeche you, as to thynke that it is dome to ſome purpoſe of ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecdte, and not all of folly, as in dede it may happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſhal hereafter ſo pereaue at large, and in the meane time I pray you accept the ſimple verſes folowynge, as my frendely
<pb facs="tcp:15297:24"/>token, and ſo wyſhynge you as to myſelfe bothe in lodgynge and otherwyſe, hartely face ye well.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The wiſe fathers of old haue alwais tought</l>
                     <l>That we ſhulde not ſhewe vnto our foo</l>
                     <l>The pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>uenes of our ſecrete thought</l>
                     <l>Though in our hart, we ſuffer deadly woo</l>
                     <l>But here it forth as if it were not foo</l>
                     <l>For our dicomfor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhal cauſe him to be glad</l>
                     <l>Where as our wyl is, for to make hym ſad.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But reaſon alas, in me is ſo appalled</l>
                     <l>That I can not vnto ſuch councell fall</l>
                     <l>Thogh in my letter I haue righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> now aſſaid</l>
                     <l>And falſely my ſelfe a diſſembler did call</l>
                     <l>Bicauſe that you my deadlyeſt foo of all</l>
                     <l>Shulde not peeceaue mine woful heuineſſe</l>
                     <l>For well I wot ye ioy at my dyſteſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yet folly nowe forceth me, the truthe for to expreſſe.</l>
                     <l>What ſo euer my letter doth conteyne</l>
                     <l>Wherfore with woful hart I ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly confeſſe</l>
                     <l>Howe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your loue hath put me to ſuch peine</l>
                     <l>That with the lyfe I may no more ſuſteyne</l>
                     <l>And if there be no grace but that I ſhalbe ded</l>
                     <l>Yet this ſhalbe my laſt, God ſend you well to wed.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15297:24"/>
               <head>Of Idleneſſe. ¶ Here Bawdyn wrytynge to a certeyne Gentleman (his frende) amonge other thynges, bewayleth hym ſelfe of his euyll ſpede in wooynge and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of mariage. The .ix. Chapter.</head>
               <p>MAſter D. After my very har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, truſtynge that ye are paſt the danger of this late vniuerſal ſickeneſſe, the newe ſweare, theſe ſhalbe to aduertiſe you, that euen ſo am I, and that with as much peryll of lyfe as euer man eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped, howe be it all for the beſte as it hath chaunced, for wheras before tyme, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my age and euyll dyete, my complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was playne malynedlyke, mixed with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer muche coller, nowe by this meanes the vnkyndly heates are ſubpreſt, and all euyll humours ſo expelled, that (the blud tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tately alayed with ſteume hauynge maſtry) I am turned to as goodly a Sanguyne as euer ye ſawe, and therewithall growen as full of loue, as any noppy newe alt is ful of barme, the croppe wherof, muche after the ſelfe ſame ſorte (ſauynge not altogether ſo hygh a lof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e) worketh, couetynge vent and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eraunce, neuertheleſſe I am determined not to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>part therwith, but onely vnder the
<pb facs="tcp:15297:25"/>blylfull bande of matrymony, whiche holy and pleaſaunt ſacrament, bycauſe I wyl no ther raſhely enter into, nor yet baſhefully (for any refuſe at a fewe handes) gyue ouer. I haue with good aduyſement made a kalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of all ſuch maydens, and wydowes (in theſe partes) as can content me that waye, whiche in the whole together with an olde fellowes wyfe, that I dare ſaye wyll not lyue out this next Marche, are to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of .xi. Vpon which appointment I haue not ſhewed my ſelfe to be ſo nyce or daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to pleaſe, as to alowe, none other but onely ſuch as are cleane without any faulte, for feare leaſt then I ſhulde not haue ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall a choyſe in ſo ſmall a circuite, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conferrynge theyr euyll tatches with theyr good qualities, I haue accepted or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, accordyng to the more parte or grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number, hauynge reſpecte therewithall for myne owne aduauncement, that one pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fytable commoditie ſhal counteruayle to euyl properties, vnleſſe they be of certeyne nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fortes, which are not to be borne withal. And more ouer preuentynge leſte my tender ſimple hart myght happen to bruſie for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe of a repulſe, if I ſhulde laye all my whole loue and good mynde in one of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t once, and then be refuſed, I haue taken
<pb facs="tcp:15297:25"/>this order in my ſute. When I am ſomwhat well entered in communication of maryage, with the fyrſt, then after two or three mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges, and before I demaunde to haue any directe aunſwere there, I begyn to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne the ſeconde, and when I haue noted in her ſome one thynge or other to my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentacion that the other hathe not, then ſtreyght wayes I returne to knowe her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate mynde, which although it be not agreable to mine, I greately force not, for then I ſtande in hope to be aſwell ſpedde or better of the ſeconde, and ſo proceadynge in lyke maner with her, I go to the thyrde, alwayes reteynynge one within poſſibilitie of ſpede, vnder this fort I haue alredy per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uſed .vii. of my number, and yet fedyng my fantaſy with hope that the beſt is behynde, my hart remayneth as freſhe and whole as when I fyrſt began. But yet by ſaynt Mary lyke as it ſhalbe wyſe dome to caſt the worſt before it fall, ſo I conſider that and yf my fortune be ſo euyll, that for lacke of ſkylfull interteynement I ſhulde chaunce to fayle al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the reſte, I doubte it wolde brynge me into ſuch perplexitie and ſorowe, as I ſhall then be neuer able to expell, for daungers once growen to thextremitie, are ſeldome or neuer reconered, and therfore ſyr I ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yre
<pb facs="tcp:15297:26"/>you ſo muche to aſſiſte me herein, as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>certeyne me by your letter, vnder what ſort ye vſyd your ſelfe, vppon obteynynge in lyke ſute, that I may ſomewhat practiſe the ſame, wherein for lacke of power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence you otherwyſe, of this ye maye be aſſuryd, myne gotten by your meanes (as re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon is) ſhalbe at your commaundement, and ſo hartely fare ye well.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Where as Bawdyn ſerued in Garryſon, and had compounded with a certeyne Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, his frende, to repayre thyther at all tymes of daunger, the ſame being ſo ſireigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in a tyme of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>motion, that he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for his ſafegarde to take another howlde, where as were many Gentle women, whiche kynde of furnyture the other greatly wanted, here Bawdin maketh him requeſt to haue ſome fruition of that neceſſarye commoditie. The .x. Chapter.</head>
               <p>The rather to allure you for to ſatyſfye my neceſſitie, hauynge preſentely a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne kynde of lacke, I haue thought good that ye ſhulde fyrſt be aduertyſed how well I intended towardes you, yf ſo were
<pb facs="tcp:15297:26"/>that for your part ye had neded of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is none other, but that my lodgyng was prepared to receue you, and my force in redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for your defence, yf ye had liſted to haue drawen hyther nowe in this daungerous tyme, accordynge to the tenure of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and olde bande of amitie. My well meanynge wherein, I craue not to be recom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>penſed with any golde or coſtly iewell. But (by your mediation) with the preſence and fauour of ſome one of your fayre Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men (whereof as I here ſaye, ye haue plentie and ſpare) of intent that being nowe forced to be a man of warre, in very dede, wheras heretofore, I haue bin but as it were a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe therof, I may wax in loue, and be va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liaunt, wherby the rather not onely to with ſtande, but alſo to ſubdue theſe vnruly and diſobedient people that manaſe to aſſaulte this Garryſon, beinge a place I aſſure you, not onely pleaſaunt and of greate ſtrengthe both by buyldynge and ſituation, but alſo plentuouſly furniſhed with men, munitions, and al other thynges requiſite for the wars, that grace of amoures only excepted, which beinge had kyndely of it ſelfe, and not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed nor peruerted with the bande of wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, is to a man of warre as a ſpurre to a dull or ſlowe horſe. Or to expreſſe more
<pb facs="tcp:15297:27"/>lyuely, well nere as greate an increaſe of holde and forwarde harte, couetynge hyghe enterpryſe, to obteyne honeſt eſtimation and fauour at his myſtres handes, as drery wed locke appallynge the lyuely ſpirites prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth cowardry. And yet to ſay trothe I haue ſometyme knowen wedded men in warlyke affayres do ryght boldely and well, but that hath byn by waye of deſperation, choſynge rather to dye, yf Fortune wolde aſcent, then longer to liue vnder ſuch yoke of ſeruytude, from the which our Lorde delyuer you, and preſerue me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The aunſwere made to the ſayde leter. The .xi. Chapter.</head>
               <p>AFter my very harty commendations, theſe ſhalbe to aduertyſe you that I haue receaued your letter, and by the ſame do playnely perceaue your faythfull frendeſhyppe ment towardes me, greatly to my comforte and reioyſyng, but not as who wolde ſaye, for that nowe in extremitie and iuſt tyme of tryall, I ſhulde haue conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to fynde my ſelfe in your behalfe, aſſured of that which before tyme I ſtode in doubte of, but rather for that it doth nowe expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apeare, that my wyttes and iudgement,
<pb facs="tcp:15297:27"/>wherof before tyme I doubted hath ſerue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> me a ryght, in choſynge ſuche an carneſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> frende as ye are coniecturynge of you afore hande, as iuſtly hath folowed. Which to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence with the beſte of my lyttle power, ye ſhall at al tymes be aſſured of. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe as to ſatiſfye your requeſte in that ye wryte, concernynge my Gentlewomen, whereof in dede I haue plentie, and ſpare, (as cauſe reaſonable ſhall requyre) I can do you no pleaſure therein, for as ye knowe it muſt nedes be done by theyr owne conſente, and reſteth not in me to apoynte, hauyng no further charge, but to the defence of theyr perſons. Howe be it for trothe I haue in your behalfe had communication with ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry of them, aſwell Ladyes as other, of whom I haue receaued ſundry aunſweres, for ſome of them ſay that if your demeanour were good, it is lykely that ye myght be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted nere home, whereas ye are better knowen, and not forced thus to ſue in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reyne partes, and ſome ſay that they are vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>certeyne whether of bothe may be moſt myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lykte, your crabbed face or your croked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and ſome of them ſaye, that they diſdayne to take the refuſe of ſo many, as heretofore ye haue bin ſuter vnto, and ſome alſo ſayth, that ye are ſo ſpente with age
<pb facs="tcp:15297:28"/>and trauayle, that to theffect of theyr moſt nede, they thynke that they ſhulde be but de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaued with you. This is as much as I can hytherto get at theyr handes, but that they acquyte your gentle requeſt, with theyr har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thankes, faythfully promyſynge to do theyr beſt for your ſpede elswhere, ſo it be not on any of theyr frends, and in affirming the ſame, haue hereunto euery of them ſet theyr handes, and ſo ryght hartely fare ye well, wyſhynge that the lawes were of ſuch lybertie that euery man myght beſtowe his owne as hym ſelfe lyſteth, for then I know where ye ſhulde for a tyme be well pleaſed, and your very frende thereby much eaſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Here Bawdyn replyeth to the ſame, and perceauynge his continual euyll ſpede, determineth to gyue ouer al ſuch kynde of ſutes. The .xii. Chapter.</head>
               <p>IF I were ignorant of myne owne impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimentes, and euyll fortune, or forgetful of that I dayely haue in remembraunce, (which for trothe, more then the number of mine yeres, haſteth me to my graue) ye ſhuld haue done but well, vppon the aunſwere of my late letter, to expreſſe my faultes, and
<pb facs="tcp:15297:28"/>ſufficient cauſe of refuſe, at your Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman handes, as ye haue done, and yet conſyderynge as the tyme nowe requyreth, that we are of all ſydes forced to prepare and faſhyon our ſelues for the warres, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in bolde and aduenturous harte (who neuer ſheweth ſo wel, as where there is a pleſaunt and amorous mynde) reſteth for a principall parte, it ſhulde haue byn good pollicie for al men (in mine opinion) not onely to diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and beare eche one with the folly and faultes of other, leſt contrary might hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pen to engender eyther frowarde controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, or feble penſiuents, but moreouer euery man for his owne parte to fede and ſtartes them ſelues with ſome kynde of vanitie or vainglory, without hauing any reſpect to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, or not deſeruing, which in dede depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth much vpon the vaine tryffles and toys of women, beinge a kynde of creatures, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſcarce worthy to be accompted as re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonable, &amp; rather an impediment vnto man, vpon matters of grauitie or importaunce, then any furtherer, yet to encorage battel &amp; like miſchiefe, a very handſome &amp; wouderful neceſſary inſtrument, which was the onely cauſe (the tyme thereunto nowe ſo requiſite) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I made requeſt to haue ſome one of yours, for to reuine my dull ſpirites, beinge mortis
<pb facs="tcp:15297:29"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yed with contemplation, to ſtyrre vp, and make the ſame more apt for feates of armes and chyualry, alterynge euery vertues qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the mynde, into ſome boldly excerciſe of actiuitie or pollicie of warre. But nowe ſythe I perceaue my felfe by your wrytynge to be thus euyll accepted, at ſo many dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete Gentlewomens handes, and for ſo ſun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dry faultes and impedimentes as by them is alleaged, I am become vtterly deſperate to obteyne in any like ſutes hereafter, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore do determine no more to attempte the ſame, but rather yf I may chaunce to eſcape the haſarde and daunger of theſe warres, to be profeſſed an Armyre, and to lyue alone in wylderneſſe, but yet for mine owne conſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation in the meane tyme, conſyderyng that the thynge whiche can not be hadde, ought wyſely to be forborne, I thought it good pollicie to perſwade my ſelfe that theyr com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany is more comberous then comfortable, and for that purpoſe dyd delyght to ſe and rede ſuche bookes as ſpake or treated any thynge to the diſpreyſe or blame of women, wheras I founde wrytten aſwell by ſundry Phyloſophers, that knowe by learnynge and natural cauſes, as alſo by other Sagies that wyſte by practiſe and experience in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and forme folowynge. Fyrſt one of them
<pb facs="tcp:15297:29"/>ſayth that they are crafty conueyers, of all maner ſhrewdnes, and ignorant innocentes in all kynde of goodnes. Another ſaythe: Blame not all women though one haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, Say well by the worſt, the beſt may be amended. Another ſayth: Of that they may haue, they ſet lyttle ſtore, And what they can not get, they longe for euermore.</p>
               <p>Another ſayth: Lybertie they couet, to do what they wyl, yet what they take in hand commenly they ſpyll. Another ſayth: What they be deſyred, they vtterly refuſe, And what they ye denayed, moſte gredely wyll they vſe. Another ſayth: Abyde by them, and they are ſone cought, But out of ſight, and out of thought. Another ſayth: For to know diuers they alwayes loue, Iudgynge hym to be beſt, which they neuer dyd proue. Another ſayth: They are diſcryuers of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and fayners of fables, Not reckynge who rolleth his dyce on theyr tables. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſayth: Wery may they be, but ſatiſfied neuer, Theyr box is incloſed in ſuch a kynd of lether. Whiche ſayinges ſoundeth moſte blyffull and comfortable to me, and as I truſt wyll ſhortly ſo crepe into my credence, and temper my deſyre towardes all women, that I ſhall thynke the beſte of them to be better loſt then founde. For ſurely all olde
<pb facs="tcp:15297:30"/>writers do thorowly agree as a very ground or principle, not to be denayed or doubted of, that the greateſt felicitie and moſte plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faunt parte of matrymonie on the mans be halfe, reſteth onely in the woynge and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treatie of maryage, wherof the Goddes be thanked, I haue ryght largely had my part and yet was always refuſed, which maketh me to thynke my ſelfe more happy then wiſe that vnder ſuche ſorte inioyinge as it were the grayne and leauynge the chaffe, I eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the harme that ſo buſely I ſought for.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The ſeconde parte of the Epiſtle ſente by Bawdyn Bacheler to Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tex Wedlocke. The .xiii. Chapter.</head>
               <p>LO Walter, nowe may ye perceaue howe deſyrous I haue byn, and what meanes I haue made to marry. For although by ſome parte of my wrytynge I ſemed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue or ſcorne ſuche as I was ſuter vnto, yet for trothe I mente to entreate or flatter them, conſyderynge that women wyll often tymes accept thynges cleane contrary, and therfore I thought beſi to proue both ways, but al wold not auayle me, for I was ſtyll refuſed, which brought me into ſuche a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitis
<pb facs="tcp:15297:30"/>and penſyuenes of mynde, that I was well nere faulne into a conſumption by playne diſpayre and malyncoly, accumpting my ſelfe the moſte vnfortunate of all men, thus to loſe with much traueyle, what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly other folkes get with eaſe, and to la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment the leſynge, of that other men repent the wynnynge. But ſuch is the frowardnes of Fortune, that to comber all men, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth peruerdy all thynges, as a wyfe to him that lacketh ſkyll howe to guyde her, and none at all to the doctours of that ſcyence. Yet at length ſearching for mine owne caſe, howe beſt to quyet my ſelfe, I dyd conſider howe God myndeth to furnyſhe heauen, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well of wyrgyns as of martyrs and other ſaynctes, iudgynge that he intendeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue me in this eſtate, onely for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, wherby to increnſe my felicitie in the worlde to come. For I remember where as Paule doth but barely alowe matrimonie, he commendeth virginite, and therefore for mine owne parte, ſyth this is mine appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted talent, I am contented to ſlande there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and frome hence forthe wyll ſeke for no change. The moſte that greueth me is, that wedded men can not now learne at my hand as I entended they ſhulde do, for doubtleſſe the myſtery of that doctrine can neyther be
<pb facs="tcp:15297:31"/>diſcloſed nor perceaued by wordes or wrye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge, ſo well as it may by ſyght of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, lyke vnto the common experience of holdynge the ploughe, which is not ſo ſone lerned by reporce, as by ſeynge the thynge done. But yet ſythen that nowe it maye be none otherwyſe, I wyl therein wryte part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mine opinion, truſtynge that it ſhall take ſome effecte, although not ſo much as I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, yf my ſute for maryage had taken place. There is a common opinion (and in dede experience oftentymes approuethe the ſame) that the thynge whiche is not well come by, proſpereth not with the owner, I meane to this effecte, men commonly nowe a dayes come not by theyr wyues as they ought to do, whiche cauſeth them to agree the worſe when they be together. For wher as they ſhulde marry for affection to the wo man and in hope of chyldren to be broughe vp in the feare and honour of God, ſurely Walter the more parte of your ſecte neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge all both, doth make of marryage as it were a for huntynge, which as you knowe is not medled withall, but when the caſe is ſomwhat worth. And then the hunter, after knowlege had where the game is, beſetteth the couert with hewers to courſe at aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ge, yf he maye preuentynge before hando
<pb facs="tcp:15297:31"/>vpon diligente inquyry made, what tochet or borowe it vſeth to reſorte vnto, as his chefe refuge, and there at thentry taketh it with a purſenet, when it thinketh to be moſt out of daunger, and ſo beinge with muche crafty pollycie and trauell gotten, is caryed home with gladnes, by common preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to playne meanyng people for loue of the fleſhe, but contrarywyſe within a very ſhort whyle the caſe is pulled of, and the carcas not eſtemed. And euen ſo it is of theſe gredy men that marryeth for the loue of ryches, without reſpect to the woman, or her quali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, who not only ſuborneth her familiers for money, in ſtede of hewers to be playne ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers, exaltynge the ſuter about all other men in ſuch quallities or habilitie, as they ſhall perceane the ſimple woman moſte to delyte, or otherwyſe perſwadeth her vnder collour of religion, as in ſafegarde of the diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers lyfe, that els wolde dye for loue, wher as in dede he neuer loued other then her ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, but moreouer preuenteth her at ſuch handes, as ſhe is moſt lykely to reſort vnto for councell, whiche crafty counceller, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he minde to further the purpoſe, yet wyll he not ſpeke therein for doubte to be ſuſpected of corruption, but when ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſike his aduyce, he is then lyke a
<pb facs="tcp:15297:32"/>purſenet, and knytteh vp the matter which ſone after is repented. For the good man regardynge none other but onely the thynge that he chefely ſought (which was the good and lande) eſtemeth not the wyfe, and then ſhe fyndynge her ſelfe diſceaued of the loue and good mynde that ſhe loked for, caſtethe to ſhorten his days by anger and diſpleſure, truſtyng to ſpede better next. And ſo mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages diſorderly begon, haue commonly com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brous continuance, and an euyll ende, I make this lyttle dygreſſion Walter to put you in remembraunce, ageynſt your next ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryage, if you come therto, for ſurely by that ye ſurmyſe that I haue an euyll opinion of maryage, I ſuſpecte that eyther you feele the ſame diſcommodities your ſelfe, &amp; that you wolde gladly haue me to be in like caſe, or els you are lyke to the greedy ryche man, that is lothe to haue any poore neyghbours, yet not for any charitie that is in hym, but rather for feare leaſt they wolde be borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. What I meane hereby I doubt not ye knowe well inough. And nowe to theffect of my promes which was to inſtruct you howe men myght lyue moſte quyetely with theyr wyues. You muſt fyrſt vnderſtande (Walter) that notwithſtandynge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all the euyll proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and ſhrew de tatches that euer were writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:15297:32"/>of women, yea or that is in them, in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dede (whiche for trewth is muche more then conueniently may be expreſſed) yet are they not therefore to be blamed or founde faulte withall, by reaſon the ſame is gyuen them euen of very nature, whoſe gyftes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge in maner forced of neceſſitie (be they good or euyll) deſerue neyther prayſe nor blame. For ſythe the tyme that the ſerpente tempted Adam and Eue, in the ſimilitude &amp; lykenes of a woman, doubtleſſe the fraude and mallyce of that ſpirite, hathe alwayes bin moſt incident to the ſame ſects, &amp; maketh them naturally inclyned to diſſimulation, in conſtancy, and frowardnes, with a number of other vyces. But what of that, ſhuld we exclude them from our company as vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, or ſhulde we diſdeynefully accept them (accordynge to the common terme) as euyll neceſſaries, or ſhulde we (beinge worſt of al) as myſtruſtyng that the Gods were not able to worke therein ſufficientely them ſelues, take on vs to alter them by arte. As before this Virgyl (whoſe preſumption was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by death) For he after ſuch tyme as he hadde atchened many ſtrange and defuſe concluſions, enterpryſed to make glaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde the hammer, determyuynge ſone after to make all women conſtant in lone, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formable
<pb facs="tcp:15297:33"/>to the wyll and pleaſues of theyr huſbandes, and al by arte magyke and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, nay nay gods forbyd. And what then, mary let vs conſider, that lyke as there is nothynge in earth ſo thorowly good, but that to ſome purpoſe, and after ſome ſorte vſed, it may be euyll. That euen ſo there is nothynge of his owne nature ſo euyll, but that to ſome purpoſe, and after ſome ſorte vſed, it may be good, and yet this hope we haue of women aboue all other thinges. The great god hym ſelfe vpon the creation of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam (as apeareth in Geneſis) ſayde, let vs make man an helper, and then made Eue, of whom al other women are deſcended, which proueth that being ſkylfully vſed, they muſt nedes be helpynge and comfortable to man, for God neuer lyeth, and then me thynketh conſyderynge that the matter toucheth the quyet of mans perſon ſo hyghly as it dothe, it is moſte neceſſarye that men ſhulde applye theyr wyrtes to ſerche out the ryght vſe of them, ſo as they maye iuſtely ſerue the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that God promiſed, as in dede (Walter) for my parte I haue done euen ſo, and that with a contemplatiue ſpirite, myndynge to lyue with them in maryage accordingly, and do perceaue the hole ſtate and myſtery ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, beinge diſcloſed vnto me by reuelation
<pb facs="tcp:15297:33"/>in my ſlepe, which in effect is thus. Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedes the God of matrymony, for the conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of maryed men, vpon lamentable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnt of theyr miſerable eſtate (by reaſon of theyr wyues crabbedneſſe) graunted by a certeyne braunche of heauen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y influence to dyſtyll into the harte of the bryde at euery weddynge, a certeyne kynde of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umour, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Bretians Spurfalxe, beinge as muche to ſaye as the iuyce or vapour of the rynge, and in Englyſhe named a wyues to the, a terme of longe tyme knowen, and yet but lately and to fewe men perceaued. The nature whereof is vehemently to inforce her ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ites to couer preheminence in certeine poyntes, which being obteyned and alowed her, it diſſolueth the malyce of all her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer euyll qualities, much after the common opinion, that one poyſon expelleth another. Hetherto (Walter) I ſuppoſe ye fynde lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle comfort in my wordes, for that it ſemeth they are not by this miracle any thynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, but rather altered from one euyil into another, which may chaunce is worſe, Neuertheleſſe yf you note me well, ye haue ryght good cauſe to reioyce, for hereby theis e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abbedues that by longe continuance in many diſcentes was growen to be in manes naturall, and therefore vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rable, maye be
<pb facs="tcp:15297:34"/>taken away, and in ſtede therof other things placed, that ye maye caſely expell if ye lyſte your ſelfe. I dare ſay you maruell what I meane by this circumſtaunce, and do longe to knowe the effect therof. Well, I am con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent that you ſhall ſo. Surely the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence that the wyues doth couette at theyr huſbands handes by vertue of that humour, is none other, but onele to haue lybertie in three kynde of thynges, whiche is, to ſaye what they wyll, to haue what they wyll, and to do what they wyl, wherin you know the huſbande maye eaſely bere with them, and ſurely doyng ſo, they are the moſt quyet and comfortableſt creatures, that euer were ordeyned for man. But reſtraynynge them therof, they are ſo crabbed and ſo combe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, as that there is nothynge ſo diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt as theyr company, which the diſcrete huſbande muſte by: his wyſedome conſyder, and for his more eaſe vſe them thereafter. For ſeinge that by the lawe they are al both but one body, and muſte remayne at one bed and bourde, it is not in mauer poſſible that he may longe lyue in quyet, when ſhe is tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly offended. Wherefore it ſhalbe neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for him to vſe her, lyke as he vſeth other bryttle thynges, as for example, If ye haue a very fayre drynkynge glaſſe, it is both ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb facs="tcp:15297:34"/>in vſe and pleaſaunte to the ſyght, and wyll ſo continue longe ynough yf it be ordred accordyngly, but and if by raſhenes or lacke of conſideration, you force it more then the tender nature therof may ſuffer, you ſodenly deſtroy your owne commoditie, for then wyll it breake and be worth nothynge at all. And ſurely euen ſo is it of a fayre ple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaunt and louynge wyfe, which is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt treaſure and comfort that man may haue in earth, whileſt ſhe remayneth in that eſtate and that wyll ſhe tyll her dyinge daye, yf ſhe be gentelly vſed, and left to haue her liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in theſe three thynges. For althoughs they vſe of theyr owne accorde to ſubmitte them ſelues inough, yet theyr noble hartes maye in no wyſe ſuffer to be forced nor brought into ſubiection by violence, muchs lyke for that purpoſe to the hawke, whoſe nature of all lyuynge thynges they drawe nereſt vnto, for the female kynde of them is alway moſt ſtubborne, moſt eger, and moſte apte to euyll, and yet by gentle meanes may be recleymed and brought to do much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but the Fawkener muſte beware that althought ſhe chaunce to checke, or to ſore awry and range, he may not therfure at her returne miſintreate her with any rygoure, but ſkilfully conſideryng the cauſe, as lacks
<pb facs="tcp:15297:35"/>of bathynge, or otherwyſe, muſt preuent to eſchewe the lyke, and ſo paciently ſuffering for the tyme, maye reforme and wynne her from her wylde and rammiſhe nature, by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycie and gentleneſſe. Much more reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is it then, that the huſbande ſhuld bere, and by ſuche gentle ſufferaunce qualifie the crabbednes of his wyfe. For wheras thone purpoſe ſerueth but only to meyneteyne his wayne pleaſure, thother toucheth hym moſt hyghly, both in the quyet of his perſon, and eſtimation of his name, whiche aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es is chefely to be conſydered, yea and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> (Walter) geuynge them a face of lybertie to haue theyr owne wyll in theſe three poyntes, they may by pollycy be tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to do youre, and in dede ſome of them wyll ſo euen of theyr owne mynde and free wyll: Lyke as the hawke when ſhe flyeth well and ſleeth her fowle, ſerueth her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters purpoſe and doth hym ſinguler plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and yet meaneth none other then her owne commoditie, howe be it, both theyr de lyghtes beinge bent to one effect, are ſerued vnder one Euen ſo ſome wyues are wholy of lyke inclination as theyr huſbandes, and then leſeth he nothynge at all by graunting them ſuche lybertie, for then: doynge the thynge that pleaſeth her ſelfe, ſhe in lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe
<pb facs="tcp:15297:35"/>contenteth hym. And ſome of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo are of ſuch worthy and honorable quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that they wyll ſhewe them ſelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in theyr beneuolence, as it were able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with the greate Alerander, who after ſuch tyme as he had in a daungerous battell with great peryll of his perſon, and loſſe of many men, ouercome the myghty kynge Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rus, a certeyne prince of the Indians, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge nought els but only the glory of vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and power to take what he lyſt. Recea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued hym afterwardes into anutie, and inlar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged his dominion with an other kyngdome of his owne. And euen ſo it ſuffyſeth ſuche worthy wyues onely to obteyne the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence at theyr huſbandes handes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſettynge the ſame in vet, but wyl rather of theyr mere and gentle nature inclyne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to the wyll and pleaſure of theyr huſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bandes. But in dede ſome ageyne are ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyſe in kepynge theyr prerogatyue, that thynke yf they do any thynge wyttyngely to theyr huſbandes contentacions, they leſs theyr liberties and ſhame them ſelues for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Such wynes theyr huſbandes may ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther manace, nor yet intreate, but muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe them by pollycie, as thus. Loke what he wolde haue them to do, let hym ſeme to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uette the contrary, for then thinkinge to
<pb facs="tcp:15297:36"/>ſerue her owne turne, ſhe wyll ſerue his, or els let hym get ſome geſtes to his table, that by way of talke ſhall ſurmyſe ſome other mans wyfe, which dwelleth a farre of, to vſe her ſelfe towardes her huſbande, vnder ſuch ſort as the goodman wolde wyſhe that his wyfe ſhulde do, geuynge her much praiſe and commendations for the ſame, and then wyll ſhe for very vayneglory, to purchaſe lyke report, do in lykewyſe, or els let hym cauſe ſome of her goſſyppes, whom ſhe hath in diſpleaſure (as commonly they are neuer without ſome ſuche) to reioyce and lawghe her to ſcorne, for the miſuſynge of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande, for then wyll ſhe amende onely to ſpyte her enemy withall. But (Walter) like as a crabbed Toulte muſte be rydden with a toughe byt, euen ſo yf the wyfe be to outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſhe muſte be vſed after a more ſharper ſorte, as thus. Let the huſbande fayne him ſelfe to be ſicke, complaynynge altogether in his hedde, and thereupon ſende for the phyſition, with whom he muſt be at a point before hande, who at his commyng, ſhal in open preſence make the matter lyght and put hym in comforte to do well, and then ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge her a parte, ſhewe her in ſecrete that he is wonderfully inclyned to a Franzie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſerybynge hym a ſpeciall dycie for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb facs="tcp:15297:36"/>therof, which aſwell for deynty fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, vnder pretence to ingender good blud as alſo for gentle interteynment for dout to ſtyrre vp the collericke humours, ſhalbe euen as the goodman him ſelfe had before hande deuyſed, &amp; yf afterwardes he ſhall perceaue her to breake any parte of the ſame, then muſt he ſtreyght wayes ſeme to be ſtarke ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge madde, and amonge other lyght and vnwonted partes be ſure to beate her well, and to inforce the matter, make as thoughe he wold leape out at the chamber wyndow, but let not her be to nere at hande leſte ſhe happen to helpe him onward, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath a whyle ſtormed in his rage, then let the phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſition come ageyne, and blamynge the wife for breakynge his order, ſeme to pacyfy him by medicine, yet fyrſt hardly let hym be well bounde, euen after the ryght Bedlem faſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but let it not be to ſtreyght, leaſt finding hym at ſuch aduantage, ſhe happen to be euen with hym, and afterwardes when he is well come to hym ſelfe, and informed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what maner he miſintreated his wyfe, let hym vtterlydenay it, as though he knew not what he had done in his woodnes, ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge and ſtarynge that and yf he wolde be ſo lewde it were pyttie of his lyfe, affirming that in al the worlde, there is not ſo beninge
<pb facs="tcp:15297:37"/>and louynge a woman to her huſbande, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that ſo lyttle doth de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erue to be vnder ſuch ſort vſed, but at length when by his wyues teares, her broken eye, her blacke ſydes, and ſore bones, he muſt nedes be perſwaded that it was trewe, then muſte he counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyte ſuch woful repentaunce, as though he ſhulde ſtreyght wayes out of his wyt ageine for pure ſorowe, wyſhynge rather to dye a thouſande ſolde, then to be vexed ageyne with the lyke paſſion. Let him vſe her two or three tymes after this forte (Walter) and I dare wa raunt ſhe wyll for her owne caſe obſerue the phiſitions order, albeit ſhe wold diſdayne to do the ſame at her huſbandes ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poyntment, but the huſbande nereth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware and handle hym ſelfe wyſely in thoſe poyntes, for and if ſhe chaunce to eſpye his fetche, ſhe is incurable for euer, lyke vnto the For, which being once tangled in a trap and eſcapeth, wyll be ſo e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rcumſpiete, that he is neuer taken by any kynde of engine af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terwardes. Sundrye other meanes and ſleigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es there is to qualifie t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e rygoure of theyr lyb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtie, whiche yf the huſbande do conſyder and wyttely prouyde for, theyr company (be they neuer ſo euyll) is tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ynough. But Walter in any wyſe, and as you inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de to eſchewe the danger of all
<pb facs="tcp:15297:37"/>theyr whole naturall malyet, looke yeſt ſwarue not from your principle, as to ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue theyr wyl in tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thre thinges, or els at leaſt waye, ſo to vſe them, as they maye thynke they haue it, for ſurely the ſame is ſo incident vnto them that tyll tyme they haue obteyned it, they are neuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, nor in maner of ryght mynde or trac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and that once alowed them, they are quyete ynoughe, and framable to manye good purpoſes. Thus Walter I haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed my promeſſe, which was to inſtruct you howe the huſbande maye beſte vſe hym ſelfe to lyue quyet with his wyfe, I praye God all your ſect may perceaue and folowe it wel, which I thynke they ſhulde do much the better, yf I confirmed my doctryne by ſome lyuely example of experience, but that can I not do in ought that chaunced vnder the yoke of matrymonye, by reaſon I haue had no practyſe that way, neuertheleſſe to make you vnderſtand, that by gentle meanes and good pollicie, there is commoditie to be had at womens handes, whiche rygoure or violence ſhal neuer ob eyne. I wyl ſhewe you an example, whereunto I was ſomewhat pryuie, that happened of late betwene a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne Gentleman and Genglewoman, both beinge of myne acquantaunce, &amp; was thus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15297:38"/>
               <head>¶ Here Bawdyn to proue that women are neuer ſo muche addicte or bente to theyr owne wyll and opinion, but that by wyſedome and good pollycie, they maye eaſely be broken thereof. Sheweth a lyuely example of late experience. The .xiiii. Chapter.</head>
               <p>ON a tyme a Gentleman of the Weſhe partes (who ſhalbe nameleſſe) at Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge Croſſe in his waye home wardes from London (then called Troynouant) ouer toke a certeyne fayre Myſtres, whom when he had ſaluted, and by communication dyd perceaue that ſhe ſhulde ryde foure or fyue dayes in his company, he was wonderfull gladde therof. For beinge hym ſelfe a cocke of the game, he thought her to be a henne of the ſame ſorte, and truſted well to haue ſome iolly good treadynge by the way. And therefore after a lyttle acquayntaunce, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded her whether ſhe coulde be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to auowe and vſe her ſelfe as his wyfe in that iourney or not (which wordes neuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theleſſe, were vttered vnder ſuch ſort, that and if his motion were not well taken, all was ſpoken but in ſport) whereunto ſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſemblyng as though ſhe miſunderſtode him,
<pb facs="tcp:15297:38"/>(and the rather by ſome penſiuenes appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge in her perſon, to perſwade hym that ſhe was not apt to receaue ſuche in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erteyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ſayde, that in dede ſhe had byn a wife but as then was none, nor neuer wolde be. And thereupon takinge occaſion to ſpeke of her deade huſbande, ſemed as thought ſhe wolde ſhortly haue folowed hym for pure ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, which when this gentleman by good exhortacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had ſomwhat appeſed, &amp; then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a lyttle pawſe reſited ageyne theffect of his former wordes, promyſyng that &amp; yf ſhe wolde ſhewe hym ſo muche gentleneſſe, he wolde not onely beare her expenſe, but moreouer be glad to ſhewe her any kynde of pleaſure that ſhulde apperteyne to the dew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of an huſbande for the tyme. Whereunto ſhe beinge then in maner forced to make dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte aunſwere, with ſober countenaunce ſayde. Alas howe haue I reioyſed without cauſe, for wheras beinge a ſtranget in theſe partes, I thought it a comfort to mete with company, the ſame to haue ſo euyll opinion of me, as to demaunde ſuch queſtion, is moſt to my diſcomfort, and therwithal proteſted before Godde that ſhe neuer was woman of that conuerſation, nor neuer wold be. Then the Gentleman leauynge to his fyrſt aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, ſware that he durſt depoſe the ſame in
<pb facs="tcp:15297:39"/>her behalfe, and that he ſpake but in borde to paſſe away the tyme, deſyrynge her not to be offended therwith. Howe be it for al that, he intended not ſo to gyue ouer his en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terpryſe, but determined to proſecute the ſame by another meanes, and thereuppon thought good to do as men commonly vſe to do with ſicke folkes, that (for lacke of appetite) when they are axed whether they wyll haue this meate or that made redy for them, they vtterly refuſe it, wheras beinge a cawdell or other good morſell, if without ſuch queſtioninge it be made redy &amp; brought them, the pleaſaunt ſauour or ſyght there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, wyll prouoke theyr ſtomakes to receaue it, therfore although beinge after this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner refuſed, yet he thought yf he myght mete her in conuenient place with his thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in redyneſſe, he had good truſt to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, for the common prouerbe ſayth, that women loue better to haue it, then to heare ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke of it, and therupon determined by ſum one pollycie or other to mete her warme a bed, and then to profer it without makinge of any queſtion or demaunde. But fyrſte as the phiſitions vſe to gyue preparatyues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they miniſter the ſubſtaunce of theyr me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicine. Euen ſo bycauſe he wolde the better be alowed when he came, he enterteined her
<pb facs="tcp:15297:39"/>before hande with all kynde of gentleneſſe, for at her Inne ſhe lacked not wyne, ſpyce, nor no other thynge that he might perceaue ſhe coueted to haue, nor no gellyes, or other confections that were good to make her coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyſhe hote or apt to receaue what he mente towardes her, and by the way to helpe her vp and downe, or to amende any thyng that was amyſſe about her, her owne ſeruaunte was not ſo attendaunt as he, ſo when he had by ſuch expenſes and dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, brought him ſelfe in ſome credite and fauour, then to gyue hee ſome warnynge before hande, leſte ſhe ſhulde abaſhe to much at his commynge. Amonge other pleaſaunte talke, he ſhewed her howe he doubted that he was not well chryſtened, for as he ſayde, he vſed often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes to ryſe out of his bedde in his ſtepe, and goynge aboute the houſe, ſhulde do he wyſt not what hym ſelfe, and that when he were in ſuche caſe, he myght go whyther ſo euer he wolde, for there was nother locke nor barre but wolde open ageynſte hym, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horſtynge her therfore, that and if he ſhulde happen to be vexed with that paſſion in her companye, and come into her chamber by nyght, that ſhe ſhulde not be afrayde therof, nor make none outcry, for he vſed not to do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny harme at all, At whiche woordes ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:15297:40"/>laughed and ſayd, that and if he came ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe wolde ſo ſcorge hym with her rod, that he ſhulde repent his commynge. The nyght folowyng (beinge in the Sommer tyme) they came to Saliſbury, where as this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man determined to ſet in vre theffecte of his deuyſe, and after ſupper, perceauynge the Gentlewoman gone into the garden with the wyfe of the houſe, and her ſeruaunte in the ſtable, leauing her chamber dore abrode, he made his ſeruaunt pryuie of his mynde, and bad him locke faſt his chamber dore, as though he had byn gone to bedde, and then ſecretely gettynge into the Gentlewomans chamber, hyd hym ſelfe vnder her bedde, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendynge when ſhe were a ſtepe, to get in by her. And ſo deuyſynge in his mynde what a buſye nyght he ſhulde haue, thought it good ſomewhat to refreſhe hym ſelfe before hande, and ſo fell a ſtepe, durynge whiche tyme there came into the ſame Inne one of ſyr Ogter Penkeyls ſeruauntes, who when he was alyghted, perceauynge the doore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode, came ſireyght into the ſame chamber and leauynge his capeaſe there, locked the chamber dore, and toke the key with hym, which when the Chamberlayne perceaued, he made requeſt to haue it ageyne, ſaying<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that he coulde not lye there, for that the
<pb facs="tcp:15297:40"/>come was otherwyſe appoynted, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the tother aunſwered that the ſame had alwayes wont to be his chamber, and there wolde he lye who ſo euer ſayde nay, vnleſſe he were fet out by the eares. In ſo muche that the Chamberleyne knowynge hym to be a common geſte of the houſe, and a fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde felowe, was loth much to ſtryue with hym, and therefore ſhewed the matter to the Gentlewoman (ſomewhat blamyng her ſeruaunte for leauynge the dore open) and deſyred her to take another chamber, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhe was ſone intreated and dyd ſo. And when tyme came gate her to her bedde, as in lyke wyſe the ſeruynge man to his, all this whyle the Gentleman lyinge vnder the bedde faſt a ſlepe, and knewe nothynge of this alteration. About midnyght he awaked and harkenynge whether he coulde here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny folke ſterrynge about the houſe, hard no thynge ſaue one ſoftely drawynge breathe within the bedde, which he ſuppoſed vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be the Gentlewoman, wherwithal his hart tyckled for ioye, which ſtreyght wayes was turned to hygh diſpleaſure. For as he came forth from vnder the bedde, thinkyng to vnray him ſelfe, he ſtumbled on the cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber potte, and made ſuche a noyſe that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erurynge man ſodenly awaked, and vnder a
<pb facs="tcp:15297:41"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ough ſorte aſked who was there, when the Gentleman contrary to his expectacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hard a mans voyce, he was wonderfully abaſhed, but yet (coniecturinge that it was the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomans ſeruaunt abedde with his myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res) he boldely anſwered and ſayde, it is I the good felowe that haue rydden ſo longe in your company (Myſtres I ſpeke to you, al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>though it be your ſeruaunte that aſketh me the queſtion) &amp; nowe to ſhewe you the cauſe of my commynge hyther, the troth is, I ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pected that ye were not ſo clere in your ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, as you wolde ſeme to be accompted by your wordes, for the profe whereof I haue purpoſely watched you, and nowe do perceaue what ye are. When the ſeruinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man harde this ſtraunge aunſwere, not knowing what the matter ment, he thought it was ſome naughty felowe that came to pycke his purſe when he were a ſlepe, and that nowe perceauynge hym to be awaked, wolde counterfepte hym ſelfe to be a foole, the rather to haue his miſdemeanour borne withall, and thereupon leapynge out of his bedde to his weapon, cryed out, theues, theues, and made ſuch a noyſe, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a whyle the goodman of the houſe, and all thother geſtes, brake open the chamber dore, and with torche lyght and clubbes
<pb facs="tcp:15297:41"/>came into theym and aſked what was the matter, wherof beinge aduertiſed by the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>claration of the ſeruyngeman (who myſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge the purpoſe that was ment, made the act very heynous) Gogges body maſter Ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheler ſayde the good man, lyttle nede had you to vſe your ſelfe ſo in this houſe, for by the holy maſt I wolde rather haue layde al the plate in my houſe at gage for you, then that ye ſhulde lacke money if I had knowne it. Gramarcy myne Hoſte ſayd the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but to make you perceaue that I had no ſuche nede (the rather thereby to iudge that I ment no ſuch thynge) ye ſhalbe pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie with my purſe, and therewithall ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the ſame, ſhewed forth in money and iewels, to the value of .xx. or, xxx. pounde, and then ſayde, ſyth the matter is come to this poynt, I wyll nowe out of hande ſhew you the thynge that I thought not to ſpeke of tyll that lent were come, that I ſhulde meete with my gooſtly father, and therupon (geuynge money to the reſidue of the compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny to depart, and drynke a gallon of wyne for theyr paynes) he toke the good man of the houſe and the ſeruyngeman aſyde, and ſhewed them the whole circumſtaunce of his purpoſe and intent, wherat when they had a whyle well laughed (exhortynge hym to
<pb facs="tcp:15297:42"/>vſe more circumſpection in the matter at his next lodgynge) they departed, euery man promyſynge to kepe councell. Howebeit ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the common prouerbe, whiche ſayth that two maye chaunce to kepe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, but three neuer. Euen ſo this matter was ſo longe talked of in councell from one to another, that before fyue of the clocke in the mornyng it came to the Gentlewomans eares, who although ſhe were nothynge in defaulte, was neuertheleſſe wonderful ſory to haue it reported that ſuche thynge was ment towardes her, accomptynge that there might enter into the hearers therof ſome ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pect of her euyll, which by any honeſte wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhulde be eſchewed, in maner as muche as the very euyl it ſelfe. And therefore per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauynge that ſhe coulde not remedye what was paſt, ſhe thought yet to preuente what was to come, ſo that in the morninge when this Gentleman ſente to knowe when ſhe wold ryde, ſhe fayned her ſelfe ſicke, and ſo forſoke his company, wherwith he was not a lyttle offended, and therupon imagininge the cauſe of her ſtay, determyned to remaine all nyght at the nexte bayte, whiche was Shafteſbery, thinkynge that when ſhe had once perceaued hym paſt and gone, it ſhulde not be longe or ſhe wold come after, and euen
<pb facs="tcp:15297:42"/>as he thought ſo it chaunced, for in deede the ſame nyght ſhe came to Shafteſbery, wherof although the Gentleman were won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derfull gladde, yet wolde he not be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to her vntyll the mornynge that ſhe were a horſebacke, for feare leſſe ſhe ſhulde fayne lyke excuſe, to eſchewe his companye as ſhe had done before tyme. But in the morninge as ſone as ſhe was gone, he came daſſhynge after, and bad her good morowe, wherwith the Gentlewoman being abaſhed, made aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere and ſayde, yea, are you there, had I knowne ye were no further paſte, I wolde not haue byn thus farre forthe, that wolde God I had neuer ſene you: Why ſo myſtres ſayde the Gentleman, haue I ſhewed you any ſuch vnkyndeneſſe, that ye ſhulde haue cauſe thus to lothe my company: Nay ſaid ſhe ye haue ſhewed me none, but rather the contrary what ſo euer ye ment towardes me But as thintent of euery acte deſerueth the thanke or blame, ſo the pretence of your gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tleneſſe tendrynge to my ſlaunder (as nowe I knowe it dyd) deſerueth no thankes at all. As to ſhewe you what I meane by theſe wordes, it ſhall not nede, for I am ſure ye knowe it well inough your ſelfe, and in like wyſe doth all the countrey. What rumoure for ſhame haue ye cauſed to be made of me
<pb facs="tcp:15297:43"/>the other night in the towne behynde, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is no other talke amonge the people but of you and me, wherin although for my parte I dyd nor ment any euyll at all, yet am I aſſured by your meanes not to eſcape ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and therwithal gan piteouſly to wepe. When the Gentleman perceaued the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter taken in ſo euyll parte, he was ryght ſo ty, but yet ſomewhat recomforted ageyne bycauſe ſhe wepte (for commonly the ſpyte and diſpleaſure of a woman wereth awaye with her teares, ſo that when thone is ſpent thother is paſt, and ſhe then much more trac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table to any frendely purpoſe then afore) whertupon after a lyttle counterfeyte e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge to be aduyſed how to excuſe him ſelfe, he thought beſte, ſythe his doynges in the matter were ſo apparaunt that it coulde not be denayed, that yet he wolde denaye any euyll of his parte mente thereby, or of hers receaned. And then ſayde, I wyſſe myſtres whereas ye ſaye that I haue cauſed you to to be ſlaundered, yf ye vnderſtode aryght, there coulde neuer thinge chaunce better for the declaration of your honeſty, then for me to come into your chamber vnder ſuch ſorte as I dyd, for wheras it myght be ſuſpected that there was ſome miſdemeanour vſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene vs (rydynge together as we haue
<pb facs="tcp:15297:43"/>done) nowe that it is perceaued home I durſt not profer to come vnto your bed, but by ſtelth and vnknowen vnto you, the ſame ſuffiſeth for your declaration in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, for all men may iudge that and yf ye had byn pryuie, or aſſentynge therunto, I wolde haue come in more boldely, ſo that in my mynde, there coulde neuer thynge haue happened better for your purpoſe, then for me to do as I dyd, and as to thynke that I entended you any euyll by my commynge, by the bleſſed Godde I mente you no more harme, then to mine owne body, wherefore good myſtres I pray you quyete your ſelfe, and be not thus offended without cauſe, no more harme then to your owne bodye ſayde ſhe? no, I thynke wel that, howebeit what ſo euer ye wolde to your owne body, I am ſure ye ment thereby none honeſty towardes me. As I be ſaued ſayde he, I ment you no diſhoneſty at all, and nowe to ſhewe you my mynde further, ſythe the matter is come to this paſſe, on my fayth miſtres I neuer in al my life knew what loue ment tyl time I met with you, why and do ye knowe now what it meaneth? ſayde ſhe, yes myſtres yes, much more to my payne, then I haue as yet byn acknowne of ſayde the Gentleman. For doubtleſſe your comely perſon and diſcrete
<pb facs="tcp:15297:44"/>demeanour hath ſo drawen myne affection towardes you, that without your preſence and fauour, it is not poſſible for my lyfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whyle to endure, and ſurely to ſhewe you therof in ſecret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſomewhat to be ſatyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed therin, was the onely cauſe that made me attempt the commynge to your bed, and for no diſhoneſty at all as Godde ſhalbe my iudge. A well ſayde ſhe, nowe I perceaue it ſhalbe an eaſy thynge to proue you eyther a diſſembler or a lyer, or els bothe. For and yf ye ſay ye loue me, and do not, then are ye a diſſembler, and on thother ſyde, yf ye do loue me and wolde come to my bedde (as ye ſay your ſelfe, to be ſaryffyed in loue) the ſame doth imply as much as to diſhoueſt me, and therfore to ſay ye ment me no diſhoneſty though the terme be rude ye are therin but a lyer. Alas myſtres were it then your dyſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty that I ſhulde imbraſe and kyſſe you abedde ſayde the Gentleman, yea but ment you none other thynge ſaue onely ſo, ſayde ſhe? Why no by the bleſſed ſacralente ſayde he, and yf I dyd or do intende, otherwyſe towardes you, God let me neuer light from this horſe in my ryght wyttes. So that in concluſion, with ſwerynge and ſtaryng that he mente her but all well, and partely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of the Gentleneſſe and liberalitie
<pb facs="tcp:15297:44"/>ſhewed in that iorney towardes her, ſhe was contented the nexte nyght folowynge to leaue her chamber dore open, and to gyue hym libertie with kyſſynge and enbraſynge to do his hart an eaſe. This thynge ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, then brake they into other talke that all theyr folkes myght here to dryne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſuſpicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſo with pleaſant thoughtes paſſynge the daye, came the nexte nyght to Charde, where as ſhe was lodged at thone ende of a longe Gallery, and he at the other, and in an other chamber, whiche ſtode be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene bothe, there lay another geſt, whiche was bownde towardes London, and came in a lyttle before them (one maſter Iewegur a Gentleman of Deuonſhyre) who beinge of the other Gentlemans acquayntaunce, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with hym in the Gentlewomans cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and after ſupper walked for recreation altogether into the garden, wheras after a lyttle talke, this maſter Iewegur (beinge a ſuſpicious and wyly fellowe) perceaued by countenances that his companyans coueted to haue ſome ſecrete talke, wherein to gyue them ſcope vnder coloure to loke in a lyttle boke that was in his boſome, he ſlaked his pace, but neuertheleſſe had his cares atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfe to theyr talke, and harde the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man with a ſofte voyce ſaye, loke ye kepe
<pb facs="tcp:15297:45"/>your promes for els ye ſle me, and ſhe to him yes yes, but for Goddes ſake loke ye come ſecretely. Yea thought the other: then I knowe what ye meane. Well? though I be not bydde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the banket, yet may I chaunce to haue ſome parte of the chere, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon repayrynge to them ageyne, fell into ſundry deuyſes, tyll at length a damoſell of the houſe came to the Gentlewoman, ſaying her chamber was redy, and that yf it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her to go to it, ſhe wolde brynge her to bedde, whereupon the Gentlewoman depar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, but the Gentlemen remayned there as longe as the day lyght wolde ſerue them to walke, and when nyght came drewe eyther of them to his chamber, ſeuerally watching of a conuenient tyme for one purpoſe, howe beit the ſmell feaſt had aduauntage of the bydden geſt (for by that names wyl I from henceforth call them) bycauſe he ſtode ſo in the way, that as longe as any ſteryng was in his chamber, the other had no ſafe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. At length when the ſmel feaſt percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the houſeholde abedde, and al thinges in quyete, ſauynge in the bydden geſtes chamber (for whom he was determined how to prouyde) he vnrayed hym ſelfe to his bare ſhyrte, and then takynge occaſion to loke on his ſwerde, founde faulte that the
<pb facs="tcp:15297:45"/>ſame was cankered, and then deuyſynge a meete place for ſuch a purpoſe (in the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery not farre from the bydden geſtes cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber dore) he ſette his ſeruaunt aworke with ſcourynge thereof, and in the meane tyme went hym ſelfe to the Gentlewomans cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, whereas he founde the dore open, and was frendely interteyned, but yet whether he were ſatyſfyed with kyſſinge and enbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge as was promyſed, or not, I ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what doubt bicauſe it was not he that made the promeſſe. And ſurely the ſelfe loue of our vnhappy tyme is ſuch (God amende it) that we ſhall ſeldome ſe any body forbeare his owne commoditie, for the obſeruynge of another mans promes, and ageyne yf ſhe thynkyng hym to be the ſame that made the promes, ſhulde perceaue hym to profer fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then was promyſed, yet were ſhe better to ſuffer in ſcilence, then to make any great noyſe in the reſcue, leſt it ſhulde ſownde in the eares of ſome (as in dede there lay ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers nere at hande) that not knowynge her ſimple meanynge, wolde thynke her in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faulte to ſuffer hym come ſo nere. But what ſo euer was done in the meane tyme, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, ſecretely as he came, ſo he departed, and ſhe for her parte ſuppoſinge that ſhe had honeſtely acquyted her ſelfe of her promes,
<pb facs="tcp:15297:46"/>determined for the reſidue of the nyght to take her reſt, and therfore roſe vp and ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly locked the dore after hym. So by this we maye ſe that it is not to be marueyled at, though ſome men laboure ſore, and can not thryne, and that ſome other doyng nothing at all waxeth ryche, for oft rymes Fortune gyueth one man the fruyte of anothers tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. When the bydden geſte who had longe tyme walked vp and downe in his chamber, Harkenynge here and there in abydynge his good houre, vnderſtode all thynges huſhe and ſtyll, and that there was no blynche of candell lyght in any where apearynge, then he thought tyme to ſet forwardes, and with tremblynge fote and hande, as thoughe his lyfe and death lay in balaunce, dyd euen ſo, but when he came to the Gentlewomans chamber, and founde her dore faſt (thinking then that ſhe ment onely to ſcorne hym) all his hotte loue or luſte (whether of bothe I may beſt call it) was ſodeynely turned into rage and fury, ſo that with a ſwollen harte he returned backe ageyne to his owne cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and there tumblynge on his bedde, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the reſidue of the nyght in great malyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coly and diſpleaſure. In the mornynge the ſmell feaſte departed very early without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of his leaue (as commonly all men
<pb facs="tcp:15297:46"/>knowynge them ſelues gylty, wyll be lothe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to tary longe nere theyr faulte for doubte of eſpymge, but the bydden geſt rode not tyl it was nere .viii. of the clocke, whome when he was a lyttle in his way, the Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with a fayned frownynge countenance began to chalenge and ſayde. A ſyr, I can you thanke, ye kepte well your promeſſe to nyght, a woman is well at caſe to ſet her honeſty in your handes vppon any othe (as who wolde ſay he hadde gone further then was promyſed) What ſo euer thanke ye can me for kepynge of my promeſſe (ſayde the Gentleman) I can you none at all for the breakinge of yours, and ſurely I am not contented with you, for ye vſed me verye noughtely therein, (very noghtely ſayd ſhe) I pray you why ſo? Mary layde the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, bycauſe ye made me watche a great parte of the nyght, and to proule aboute in the darke, promyſynge to leaue your cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber dore abrode and dyd not ſo. Then wyſte ſhe well that ſhe had bin deceaued, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge for a womans ſhyfte howe to ſaue al thynges vpryght, ſodeynly founde one, and ſayde: Why ſyr and were ye there in dede? and I ment to chalenge you bicauſe ye came not. Yea that was I by the good Lord (ſayd the Gentleman) euen at mydnyght, and
<pb facs="tcp:15297:47"/>founde it falſte locked. Nowe by out bleſſed Lady ſayde the Gentlewoman, then ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued your ſelfe, for my dore was left open purpoſely for you, mary there was another dore faſte by it whiche in dede was locked, and of lykelyhod for lacke of lyght ye toke the one for the other. Nowe on my fayth, ſayde the Gentleman, it was euen ſo ſure ynough, and thereupon laughynge at the matter, helde her excuſed, determynynge to vſe hym ſelfe more circumſpecrely the nexte nyght folowynge, but in the meane tyme as the deuyll wolde, there came ageynſte them a kynſeman of the Gentlewomans (to gyde her thyther as ſhe was bounden) who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyed her out of his company. And ſo by the crafty dealynge of the ſubtyll ſmell feaſte, the bydden geſt was diſapoynted of his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, whiche by the peruerſenes of Fortune without any default in the woman, he could neuer recouer afterwardes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The thyrde and laſt parte of the Epiſtle ſente by Bawdyn Bacheler to Walter Wedlocke. The .xv. Chapter.</head>
               <p>By this experiment Walter we maye (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge other thynges) perceaue thinſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie
<pb facs="tcp:15297:47"/>of womens determinations, and how by diſcrete diligence and pollicie, they may be allured whereunto men lyſt, be it good or euyll, ſo that Fortune be not vtterly bent to the contrary, as it ſemeth ſhe was ageynſte the bydden geſtes enterpryſe. For in deede then there is no remedy, as before this, the wyfe in excuſynge her ſelfe, when ſhe was blamed for geuynge her huſbande the lothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome lyuery, ſayde that ſhe coulde nat do therwith, by reaſon that it was his fortune to haue it, and was thereby very well alow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed both of Iuſtice Mynos hym ſelfe, and of all the whole courte. But Lorde God Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter howe raſhe wytted am I become of late, for had I not chaunced to fall ageyne into like matter, I ſhuld haue omytted one of the chefeſt thynges that concerneth the purpoſe I treate vppon, whiche is to preſerue the quyete betwene man and wyfe. For ſurely by ought that I can perceaue, the greateſte breache therof, is when ſhe chaunceth to lye with ſome other man, whiche thynge the huſbande in ſome countreys vſeth to take wonderfull greuouſly, and yet let the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reſt there, as in dede it might wel inough yf he were diſcrete, and then were there no harme done at all, for I haue knowen a number of men ſo vſed, and yet remayne as
<pb facs="tcp:15297:48"/>holſome in theyr bodyes, as quyete in theyr myndes, and as ſufficiently furny ſhed to all purpoſes, as yf it had neuer ſo chaunced.</p>
               <p>What is it then thynke ye that cauſeth their torment and diſtemperaunce, mary the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge therof: Why and whoſe defaulte I pray you is that, is it the wyues: Nay nay God wot, but his owne that pryeth to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue it, much lyke the mad man that ſeketh for a knyfe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le hym ſelfe. Oh vphappye plage, that commeth onely by Sathan, for nature wolde haue it kepte pryuie, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore prouoketh to haue it done in ſecrete, nor God wolde not haue it diſcloſed, and therfore ſetteth in the peoples hartes neuer to ſhewe the huſband therof, though it were ſo that al the reſt of his paryſhe ſhulde hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to knowe it, and wyl he then hym ſelfe ſeke his owne harme, and make earneſte of game. Well and if he wyll nedes be ſo foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe, let hym languyſhe with the frute ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and I ſhrewe all ſuch as wyl mone him, it is me thinketh muche lyke the eatynge of a flye blowe (beinge a certeyne kynde of ſmall wormes that is oftentymes founde in colde mutton, and ſuch lyke meates, in the ſommer tyme) wherof although a man eate a thouſande (as commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly men do when they feede hungerly, and lokethe not for them,
<pb facs="tcp:15297:48"/>yet doth it no harme at al. But and if after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes ſerchynge more narowly, he percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth by them that are lefte, that in dede he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eaten ſome. Then ſtreyght wayes he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his gorge, and maketh ado as yf he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> poyſoned, which for erothe is not for any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uyll that is in the thyng, but commeth onely of a certeine ſqueymyſhenes and imper ſection of the ſtomake. And ſurely Walter, euen ſo is it in the other matter, yea and in all bothe caſes to thynke that it be ſo, is as great diſpleaſure and vnquietneſſe of mind, as if it were ſo in dede, which declareth the inhicilitie of mans nature in that behalfe, and prouethe playnelye that it is rather a vayne quarrel of the mynde grounded on no neceſſitie, then any ſufficiente or effectuall cauſe of diſpleaſure. But yet Walter for all that, yf ye be one of theſe that can not paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently beare it (yf it ſo chaunced) then myne aduyce ſhalbe that ye neuer myſtruſte it, nor yet make meanes to knowe it, for then I dare warrance ye ſhal neuer be greued ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. Or caſt the worſt, as that ye chaunce to eſpye it your ſelfe vnloked for, yet then beware that in no wyſe ye make any noyſe or wordes therof, but kepe it as ſecrete from all other mens knowledge as ye can. For well wyſt the wytty Duyde what diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dities
<pb facs="tcp:15297:49"/>growethe by the contrarye, when he wrote the parable howe Vulcanus fynding his wyfe in bedde with Marſe, tranſformed the ſhetes that they laye betwene, by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne magytycall meanes, into a cage or net of wyer, and brought al the Gods to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who neuertheleſſe dyd but laugh hym to ſcorne for hys folly ſhewed therein, and eſtemed his diſcretion the leſſe euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Doubtleſſe a worthy example for vs to eſchewe the lyke myſdemeanoure, yf wee chaunce to come within the daunger therof, for it appereth that by ſo doyng, we get no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge els but rebuke and ſhame. No Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not ſo much as to let your wife her ſelfe perceaue that ye do knowe it, for then ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyll ſhe be abhominable bolde, ſeynge you contented to beare therewith. Or els muſt ye thinkyng to breke her from it, make ſuch a ſtyre and buſines, as all the worlde ſhall wonder at you bothe, and ſurely much better it is to diſſemble at the matter for a tyme and abyde the commynge of age, who is the common amender of all ſuche faultes, to whiche effecte I wyl ſhewe you a notable experience that chaunced of late, and was thus. In the towne of Penborgh a certeine Smyth on a tyme came to the Proueſt of the colledge there, and told him that ſyr Henry
<pb facs="tcp:15297:49"/>Polmarghe a prieſt of the ſame colledge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſortynge muche to his houſe vnder pretence of coſynage, vſed his wyfe ouer boldely. Whereunto the Proueſte aunſwered, peace Iohn Iohn, for I dare ſay it is not ſo: or and yf it be, I promeſſe thee I wyll cauſe hym to leaue it. Nay maſter ſayd the Smyth I neyther doubte of the one nor hope of the other, but my deſyre ſhalbe, that your maſter ſhyppe for my poore honeſty, wyll cauſe him to vſe hym ſelfe more circumſpectly therein then he hath done, for yeſterdaye as he and I ſat together at brekefaſt, maſter Saghers man called me forthe to ſhooe a horſe, and when I came to the clinſhing of the nayles, I myſt my pyncers (beinge in my hall wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe) which when I came to fetch, I found my wife and him interlaſed vpon my bench, vnder ſuche an homely ſorte, that on my ſayth I was aſhamed to loke on them, and thereupon wente backe ageyne before they eſpyed me, and borowed a payre of pyncers of my neyghbour. And ſyr, aſwell myght there a ſtraunger haue come in, and ſhamed me for euer, as by my trothe, yf I had byn certeyne where the pyncers hadde lyen, I wolde haue ſent maſter Saghers man in for them. And ſyr bycauſe the matter toucheth me ſo nets as it doth, I thynke it not beſte
<pb facs="tcp:15297:50"/>for me to ſpeke vnto them therein my ſelfe, aſwell for doubt I ſhall not kepe due tempe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunce in my wordes, or for ſundrye other conſiderations, nor in dede I wolde not they ſhulde perceaue that I knowe ſo much therein as I do, and therefore good maſter Proueſt make no notherwyſe vnto hym, but that ye ſuſpect it of your ſelfe vpon reporte at large, for that ſhall ſuffyce to make hym more ware and circumſpecte, whiche is as much as I loke for as yet. Nor ſyr I tel it not you, but as it were vnder confeſſion, truſtynge that ye wyll kept it ſecrete. If this rude man this Smyth that neuer redde Ouyde, nor no other good aucthor, coulde after ſuche diſcrete ſorte temper his cauſe, muche rather ſhulde they do ſo that art of more knowledge and better learned. And to you ye Venerian wyues, though ye chaunce to be narowly taken, and charged therwith, yet be well ware ye neuer confeſſe it to the death, but ſpeke and prate in your excuſe to the vttermoſte, as thoughe ye were inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in the matter. For what ſo euer the preſumption or lykelynes thereof be, yet of this ye maye be certeyne, the very effecte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth on ſo defuſe and ſecrete a poynte, that in manner it is not poſſyble to be playnely knowen, without ye wyll be ſo madde as to
<pb facs="tcp:15297:50"/>condempne your ſelues, and then farewell your good dayes all your lyfe after. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by a lyttle ſtoute ſtandynge at your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, with a ſober or circumſpecte lyfe fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowynge, ye ſhall ſone growe out of ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for this ye muſte vnderſtande, men are eaſely perſwaded to beleue the thynge, ſuch as in theyr hart they couet it ſhulde be. And for your partes ye Cupydyan knyghtes, ye muſt ieme to delyght in ſuch paſtyme and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creation, as ye ſhall perceaue the good man to do, whether it be huntynge, hawkyng, gamynge, or otherwyſe, for ſo may ye beſte growe into familiaritie with hym, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour your repayre to the houſe to be onely for his company. But then beware that your open lyght demeanour, diſcloſe not your ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crete intent, as the wenche that pretended heroften goynge to the Churche to be all for deuotion, but when it came to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> purpoſe, her affection ſo muche ouerpaſte h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reaſon, that ſhe ſet aſyde the Paxe, and kyſt the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe Clarke, wherby her mynde that before tyme was pryuate to her ſelfe, was made common to the whole paryſhe, therfore take hede that ye do not in lykewyſe, &amp; when ye lift to reward your myſtres with ſome iewel or garment, loke ye make no gyft therof, but
<pb facs="tcp:15297:51"/>leſe it vnto her vpon ſome wager, made in the huſbandes preſence. And what ſo euer the vchemency or ouerboldnes of her affecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on ſhal happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be, yet be you wel ware that ye neyther diſapoynte or interrupte hym at any ſuch tyme, as he ſhal mynde to haue her attendaunt him ſelfe, for that is odible, and wyll ſone engender ſuſpicion, and beſydes that in dede it is ageynſt all good curteſye, wherein the people of this Realme haue bin accompted to excede all other. And ſurely a chiefe part therof, is to ſuffer the good man (be he neuer ſo ſimple) to haue preheminence and chiefe attendaunce of his owne wyfe, notwithſtandynge her frendely familiaritie mente towardes any other, beinge of better abilitie or more eſtimation. Yet for my part not meanynge hereby to excyte or intyce you to any diſſolute maners or incontinent trade of lyfe, but onely your ſelues beinge bente thereunto, that then it may be ſo conneyed, as leaſt rumour and inconuenience may ther of followe, in preſeruynge the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uyerneſſe that I wyſhe to haue contynewed betwene man and wyfe, which I chiefely do for the reuerence I bere to the pleaſaunt ſacrament of matrymony, bicauſe my poore father was ſometyme accompted to be one of that band. No ſyrs, nor by ſaynte Mary I wyll not
<pb facs="tcp:15297:51"/>knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſuche enterpryſes of yours is lawful, for what ſo euer hath bin permitted vppon conſiderations in the former ages, or wrytten by the Phyloſophers or Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes of that time, yet I remember wel we haue this famylier prouerbe, of aucthoritie. (Newe Lordes, newe lawes) and therefore maye chaunce that by the commynge of Chryſte, ſuch olde rytes and cuſtomes are abrogated and then is there peryll in the vſe thereof.</p>
               <p>And alſo it ſemeth that the gyft claymed by theſe wyues from Neomenius, maketh not ſo much for theyr purpoſe as they thynke it doth, for in dede it is none other, but onely to make them cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t lybertie, for to ſay, do, and haue what they wyll, not expreſſynge that the ſame ſhalbe lawfull for them, nor yet doth not diſpence with thiniquitie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of yf it be otherwyſe. And ſurely Paule to the contrarye ſaythe, that the huſbande is the wyues hedde, and that ſhe ſhulde holde her ſelfe to hym onely, and be confirmable to his wyll, and therfore aduiſe them at theyr owne peryll, for if they choſe the wronge way, I wyll not bere the wyte thereof by abettynge them thereunto. And nowe Walter to conclude with you, wheras ye haue vniuſtly accuſed me, that I ſhulde diſpyſe maryage, I truſt I haue bothe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
<pb facs="tcp:15297:52"/>declared my ſelfe therein, and alſo gyuen you enſample of a Chryſtian charitie, aſwell in exhortynge you (notwithſtanding your raylynge rage ſhewed towardes me) howe paciently to ſuffer the harme that can not be eſchewed, as alſo in counſaylynge how the ſame may beſt be kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge and wondrynge of the worlde, which for troth in ſuch caſe is more payne and rebuke then the very euyll it ſelfe, requyrynge no more at your handes for all my traueyle and good wyll herein, but from hence forth, to haue your good worde, and ye ſhalbe ſure of myne.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15297:52"/>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Wyllyam Seres, dwellynge in Powles Churche yard at the ſigne of the Hedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hogge.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
